<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fall not out by the way, or, A perswasion to a friendly correspondence between the conformists &amp; non-conformists in a funeral discourse on Gen. 45. 24. occasioned by the desire of Mr. Anthony Dunwell, in his last will / by Timothy Rogers ...</title>
            <author>Rogers, Timothy, 1658-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57577</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1850</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11323</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11822866</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11822866</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49606</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57577)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49606)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 547:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fall not out by the way, or, A perswasion to a friendly correspondence between the conformists &amp; non-conformists in a funeral discourse on Gen. 45. 24. occasioned by the desire of Mr. Anthony Dunwell, in his last will / by Timothy Rogers ...</title>
                  <author>Rogers, Timothy, 1658-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 108 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Dunton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis XLV, 24 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Sermons --  England --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49606:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49606:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fall not out by the Way:</hi> OR, A PERSWASION TO A Friendly Correſpondence Between the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> &amp; <hi>Non-Conformiſts.</hi> IN A Funeral Diſcourſe On <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.24.</p>
            <p>Occaſioned by the Deſire of Mr. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony Dunwell,</hi> in his laſt Will.</p>
            <p>By <hi>TIMOTHY ROGERS,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, for <hi>John Dunton,</hi> at the <hi>Raven</hi> in the <hi>Poultery,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49606:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49606:2"/>
            <head>To the Gentlemen that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Evening Lecture</hi> at <hi>Crosby-ſquare.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is to you that I owe the largest acknowledgment ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable; for the kindneſſes that you have ſhewed me, have not only been in themſelves very Great, but <hi>very Singular.</hi> It
<pb facs="tcp:49606:3"/>was a Noble and a Generous Act, ſo liberally as you have done, to encourage Mr. <hi>Kentiſh</hi> and <hi>Me,</hi> and it was a Rare and Peculiar Generoſity not to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the Teſtimonies of your Love and Reſpect during <hi>my Long and Doleful Sickneſs,</hi> which made me for two Years incapable of being any way ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to you. It is impoſſible for me to forget ſo great a Favor, and equally impoſſible for me to expreſs the ſenſe I have of it.</p>
            <p>At the deſire of Mr. <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> one of your number, I Preached on the following Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
<pb facs="tcp:49606:3"/>and now at the request of a great many of the ſame number, it comes into the World: And I was the more willing that it ſhould ſee the Light, becauſe, as far as in me lies, I would help to Extinguiſh thoſe Flames, which being encreaſed by <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and ſtrangeneſs,</hi> have long Troubled and Scorched us. It is in vain, I well know, to think that all Men will have the ſame Thoughts, or the ſame Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions about matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; foraſmuch as in their <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Souls there are different degrees</hi> of Light; but I would
<pb facs="tcp:49606:4"/>endeavour however to perſwade perſons of different apprehenſions to be kind and civil and genteel to one another, and this is eaſy to be done, and will be attended with a mighty pleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Lecture,</hi> as you will bear us Witneſs, is not a Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of Sedition; nothing, we dare appeal to you and our other Hearers, is Preached there, but what is <hi>Orthodox</hi> and <hi>Loyal</hi> too; nor do we there take an occaſion to vent our own Paſſions inſtead of the Truths of God; nor at any time endeavour to make our Hearers have an ill Opinion
<pb facs="tcp:49606:4"/>of our <hi>Brethren the Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,</hi> for ſo we love to call them, and we hope they will not refuſe to give to us the <hi>ſame Friendly Title.</hi> We have among us all abundance of common Work to do againſt <hi>Atheiſm and Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs,</hi> and the other Vices of a Corrupt Age, and againſt the World, the Devil and the Fleſh: The neceſſities of the Souls of Men are ſo many, that our <hi>United Endeavors</hi> will be little enough to ſupply them; and therefore we ſhould Love and Encourage and bear with one another, and ſo the <hi>Good</hi> of all ſides, I verily
<pb facs="tcp:49606:5"/>perſwade my ſelf, will reſolve to do.</p>
            <p>In our Diſcourſes our Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory do not uſe to find matter ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of juſt <hi>Scorn</hi> or <hi>Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> nothing, I hope, that is Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd or Ridiculous. A late Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomizer of the <hi>Works of the Learned,</hi> is ſo complaiſant as to call ſome Practical Diſcourſes of mine, formerly Publiſhed, <hi>Cant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sermons,</hi> and thinks thoſe Gentlemen, who in a <hi>late Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Books,</hi> put an Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe Diſcourſes after ſome Sermons of Mr. <hi>Norris,</hi> Acted, as if by ſuch a method
<pb facs="tcp:49606:5"/>they deſigned to expoſe the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters.</hi> I will allow Mr. <hi>Norris</hi> to be an Ingenious and neat Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>his Thoughts is Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and his Language Fine;</hi> but I think it will be no diskindneſs either to him, or Mr. <hi>De la Croſe,</hi> to deſire them not to dip their Pens in Gall, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear Satyr when they would ſpread Truth: A little more good Nature and Civility would do neither of them any great harm. To ſay this or that is <hi>Cant</hi> is no Proof, 'tis Reviling without a Reaſon, and none of the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or Judicious will uſe <hi>ſo ſilly</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:49606:6"/>and ſo Trite a Word. I am afraid this <hi>French Writer</hi> is of a <hi>very little Soul,</hi> and thinks no Senſe can be ſpoken but on his own ſide: Men of more <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding than he, will allow that the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> know a little what belongs to Senſe and good Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage too. He Ridicules the <hi>Lives of Mr.</hi> Hieron <hi>and Mr.</hi> Eliot of <hi>New England,</hi> thoſe <hi>Bleſſed Divines,</hi> as he calls them, but I wiſh he may ſit at their Feet in the other World. I would deſire this <hi>Abridger</hi> of Books not to be ſo <hi>Partial;</hi> and if he would have his Writings
<pb facs="tcp:49606:6"/>to be uſeful, not to cram them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with <hi>ſuch Stuff,</hi> for it is nauſeous to all Men of Senſe and good Breeding, to ſee perſons of ſuch a <hi>Little Soul</hi> talk as if they had Monopolized all the Wit and Senſe of the World in their own Brains. I have longer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted upon this, becauſe I hope it may a <hi>little Soften</hi> ſome that are of a Moroſe and Waſpiſh Constitution: I wonder in what Air they have lived that are continually ſpitting out <hi>Ulcerated Language:</hi> I wiſh all the <hi>Men of Bitterneſs</hi> an Healthful ſtate of Soul, and then I am ſure
<pb facs="tcp:49606:7"/>they will be calm and gentle, they will ceaſe to be Incendiaries and learn to be Peacemakers, which is a much better Office.</p>
            <p>To you, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> it is that I do now publickly return my ſincere and hearty Thanks for all your Kindneſſes to me both in <hi>Health and Sickneſs:</hi> At your Service I am, and ſhall upon all occaſions be ready to give you the moſt <hi>chearful</hi> Marks of my Reſpect; may your Trades and Employments thrive better for what you give to my <hi>Brother Kentiſh</hi> and to me: What good is done to the
<pb facs="tcp:49606:7"/>Souls of Men by us (as we hope there is ſome) will turn al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to your Account in that Day: I wiſh you may continue to be <hi>promoters of Peace and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among all good Perſons of all Perſwaſions,</hi> and that you would labour in your ſeveral Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to advance a thing ſo Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and ſo Profitable: May you have always <hi>calm Spirits, and quiet Families,</hi> and loving People to Deal withal: May you have Comprehenſive and <hi>large Souls:</hi> For many long Years may you Thrive and Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and be uſeful in this World,
<pb facs="tcp:49606:8"/>and at laſt be admitted into the World above, which is the bleſſed place, for it is the <hi>World of Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>So Prays, <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>Your very much Obliged Servant, L. Rogers.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>Decemb. <hi>12th 1691.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:49606:8"/>
            <head>The following Books have been lately Publiſhed by the Author of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>PRactical Diſcourſes</hi> on Sickneſs and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, in ſeveral Sermons, as they were lately Preached in a Congregation in <hi>London,</hi> after his Recovery from a Sickneſs of near two Years continuance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Early Religion:</hi> Or, a Diſcourſe of the Duty and Intereſt of Youth, with ſome Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices to Parents and Aged People to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote it in their ſeveral Capacities.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Diſcourſe concerning <hi>Trouble of Mind,</hi> and the Diſeaſe of <hi>Melancholy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All three to be Sold by <hi>John Dunton</hi> at the <hi>Raven</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:49606:9"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 25. line 20. Read <hi>Ages poſeſed,</hi> p. 31. l. 21. r. <hi>in its ſelf,</hi> p. 71. l. 19. for <hi>of,</hi> r. <hi>in.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49606:9"/>
            <head>Two SERMONS Preached upon the DEATH OF Mr. <hi>Anthony Dunwell.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. xlv. 24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>See that ye fall not out by the way.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is not unknown to ſeveral here, That this Evening is ſolemn to us upon more Accounts than one; not only as 'tis the Evening of the Lord's Day, and the uſual Time of our Lecture here, but alſo as the Providence of God hath given us a peculiar Occaſion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49606:10"/>to remember a Departed Friend, by whoſe Appointment and Deſire, before he dyed, I am now come to Preach a <hi>Funeral Sermon</hi> for him. It is the ſame Perſon for whom, when I was laſt here, we prayed, as being then in the painful Agonies of Death; and the next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God was pleaſed to let him Dye. He had for ſeveral Months, by a Lingring Waſting Diſeaſe, found the Truth of that in <hi>Job.</hi> 14.1. <hi>That man that is born of a Woman is full of Trouble:</hi> and now his going hence has alſo given us the Proof of the next Verſe, how, <hi>he cometh forth like a flower, and is cut down: He fleeth alſo as a ſhadow, and continueth not.</hi> This Flower, on which a little while ago we looked with Delight, is now blaſted with the Stroak of Death, and we ſhall not behold its Greenneſs and Freſhneſs in this World any more: Though we hope it is tranſplanted to flouriſh in a better Place.</p>
            <p>This Friend, whoſe Funeral we now celebrate, was a conſtant Hearer in this Place, a generous Encourager of this Lecture; to my Brother <hi>Kentiſh</hi> and to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49606:10"/>me he was a Cordial and ſincere Friend; but alas, he is gone: His Death is indeed our Loſs, but we hope it was his Gain. He is gone, whoſe Friendſhip was ſo pleaſant and ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to us: He that delighted in the Activity of his ſerviceableneſs to God and us, is now at reſt in the ſilent Grave; there we hope he <hi>ſleeps in the Lord;</hi> there we muſt leave his Duſt, and thither will <hi>his Works follow him.</hi> He uſed to be a conſtant Attender on this Lecture, as he was always more than a Well-wiſher to it; and I could heartily deſire that thoſe other Young People, to whom we are beholden for their Kindneſs, would be equally Serious, and if it conſiſted with the Order of their Families, as diligent Attenders; there are ſome indeed that are ſo, and if they were all ſuch, we hope they would not loſe their Time: We would willingly have them to receive ſome Benefit by our poor Pains, and to taſte of the Fruit of thoſe Studies which their Liberalities have Promoted and Encouraged. If it had ſo pleaſed God, I had rather have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49606:11"/>come hither to have preached a Sermon of Thankfulneſs, for the Recovery of our Friend, than a Funeral Sermon: I know it would have been pleaſant to us, and to all his Relations, to have joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on ſuch a chearful occaſion; and our Praiſes then would have been as many as are now our Sighs and Tears: To theſe <hi>Mourners</hi> I am ſure the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Praiſe would have been much more delightful than theſe of Heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: But what ſhall we ſay, the Will of God is Done, and let us humbly and quietly acquieſce therein, for he alone knows when it is the moſt proper Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for us all to dye: Our Acquaintance are going into the next World, one after another, and in a little while we ſhall alſo be gone, and our Places know us no more. To thoſe that are Departed we muſt go, they will not return to us; though our Duty under the Stroaks of God, and the Loſs of our Friends ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges us to be ſenſible of his Warnings, and of our own Frailty; yet it alſo does engage us not to Repine or Murmur at his Providence. Our Eyes may juſtly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49606:11"/>weep when we ſee the Graves of our Holy Friends; but they ought not ſo to weep, as to hinder our View of their certain and approaching Reſurrection, when their now vile and conſuming Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhall be like <hi>the glorious Body of our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I believe you will think this a very ſtrange Place of Scripture, on ſuch a ſad occaſion as this; I believe, had I been left to my Liberty, I ſhould not have choſen it; but it was bequeathed to me in the <hi>Laſt Will and Teſtament</hi> of our deceaſed Friend Mr. <hi>Anthony Dunwel,</hi> and I do now underſtand, That it was that which he had fixed upon ſeveral Years ago: Men never put any thing in their Wills of this nature, but what they moſt firmly deſire to have done. It may be a great Comfort to his Friends and Acquaintance, that he not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a quiet and peaceable Spirit to his Dying Day, but that he was willing to have Peace and Quietneſs flouriſh in the World and in the Church, when he was Dead and Gone; a Temper not like to thoſe ſelfiſh and narrow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Soul
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49606:12"/>People, that ſo they may Live and Dye at Eaſe, care not if all the World be in Flames and Wars, and Confuſions after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, as he ſaid, <hi>Me pereunte ruat Mundus.</hi> Our peaceable Friend was in this Like to our Bleſſed Saviour, who as he choſe to be manifeſted when the Temple of <hi>Janus</hi> was ſhut at <hi>Rome,</hi> and all the World was in a profound Peace, and being himſelf the Prince of Peace; and his Reign full of Pity, he endeavoured to Reconcile God and Man, and the Sons of Men to one another. So, a little before his Death, diſcourſing with his Diſciples, Peace was the great Legacy that he bequeath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, <hi>Joh.</hi> xiv. 27. <hi>Peace I leave with you; my Peace I give unto you:</hi> And it is like, our Deceaſed Friend had this in his Eye when he left this Text; which is indeed a moſt pleaſant Text, though the Occaſion on which I am to inſiſt upon it be ſad and mournful, and I will apply my ſelf to the handling of it, when I have done that Juſtice to <hi>the Relations and Friends of the Deceaſed,</hi> as to ſay, That I never heard of any falling out
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49606:12"/>among them; nor is there, I fully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, any Diſagreement, but a cordial and ſincere Love, as there ought to be: Nor do I believe that he intended them, when his Thoughts fixed upon this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; but only from what I apprehend, he was greatly deſirous that there ſhould be Love, and Friendſhip, and Union, and Peace among all Good People, of whatſoever Profeſſion and Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>whether Conformiſts or Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts;</hi> and in this Senſe, and with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to this, that I ſhall now explain this good Advice, <hi>See that ye fall not out by the Way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Hiſtory of <hi>Joſeph</hi> contains a ſeries of admirable Tranſactions, and is a great inſtance of the Myſteriouſneſs and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Divine Providence, that by Ways, to Appearance very unlikely and undiſcerned at firſt by Mortal Men, does certainly bring about his own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and that Curious Succeſſion and Period of Things, which was firſt laid in his own Decree. The Malice and Envy of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethen was the Means of his Advancement; their Selling of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49606:13"/>him preſerved their own Lives: It was a Cruel Lye that they told his Father <hi>Jacob,</hi> when they ſaid, <hi>Joſeph</hi> was torn to pieces, and ſhewed the Coat of his Son, his deareſt Son <hi>Joſeph,</hi> all beſmear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Blood; What Hearts had they that could thus torment a poor Old Man, and their own Father too? and what Sorrow pierced his Heart, when he thought he had taken of him an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Farewel, and ſhould ſee the promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and hopeful Youth no more for ever? See <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.33, 34. he ſaid, <hi>It is my Son's Coat, an evil beaſt hath devoured him;</hi> Joſeph <hi>is without doubt rent in pieces. And</hi> Jacob <hi>rent his Cloaths, and put Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth on his loins, and mourned for his ſon many days.</hi> I wonder at <hi>Joſeph,</hi> that he ſhould never ſend Word to his Father that he was alive; or that when he had now ſo fair an Opportunity he ſhould ſo long neglect to give him the Tidings of his Welfare, for he might juſtly think it would wipe away all the Tears of his Mourning Father, as it did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely revive him afterwards; when he heard that <hi>Joſeph</hi> was alive, the good
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49606:13"/>old Patriarch was then content to Dye: <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.48. Iſrael <hi>ſaid, it is enough,</hi> Joſeph my Son is yet <hi>alive: I will go and</hi> ſee him <hi>before I dye.</hi> I moſt of all wonder that he ſhould urge his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to bring from their Father his only remaining Comfort, their younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the very Motion of which was ſo formidable to his Cruel Brothers, and they knew it would be ſo ſad News at home, that it immediately awakened their Conſciences for the Crime that they had committed againſt him a great while ago, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.21. And <hi>Joſeph</hi> hearing their Mutual Accuſations, was much affected with them, and was forced to turn about and Weep, ver. 24. They brought the ſad News Home, and you hear the Language of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, ver. 36. <hi>he ſaid unto them, Me ye have bereaved of my Children:</hi> Joſeph <hi>is not, and</hi> Simeon <hi>is not, and ye will take</hi> Benjamin <hi>away, all theſe things are againſt me.</hi> The poor Man thought all this was to load him with a greater Heap of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, when it was the way to make him Happy. Good People are apt to think,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49606:14"/>when many Croſſes meet together, that they are abſolutely ruined; but the Potions that are very bitter, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote their Health; and what they loſe in the Creatures, God is pleaſed to make up with his own Love, or to reſtore them Mercies of the ſame kind with thoſe of which they are now bereaved. This was a ſevere Propoſal to <hi>Jacob,</hi> and as one ſays, (<hi>Cereziers. Joſeph. or the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence,</hi> p. 109.) he may be ſuppoſed to cry after this manner; <hi>Will you bury me alive? Suffer me to Live, may be you intend to ſee me languiſh the reſt of my Days! I have one only Son, that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolates the Loſs of</hi> Joſeph, <hi>and of his poor Mother, and muſt I loſe him! O my God, how happy had my Condition been, to have had no Children, or to have had ſome more proſperous! I have then had but my Miſeries to bewail; whereas now I ſee my ſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to take the beſt part of thoſe that inflict them:</hi> Joſeph <hi>hath ſatisfyed the Cruel Hunger of a Savage Beaſt; and his Brother, to appeaſe ours, muſt be expoſed to the Deſire of a Barbarian, who perchance may take Pleaſure to torment me in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49606:14"/>Perſon of</hi> Benjamin. <hi>What know I if he obliged not all my Children to preſent themſelves to him, to involve them under one and the ſame Ruin, and to blot out the Name of</hi> Iſrael <hi>from the Earth?</hi> In the 43 Chapter you behold, That this <hi>Joſeph,</hi> that had carried it ſo politickly toward them for a long Time, does at length begin to melt, v. 29. his Pity and his Joy made him ſcarce able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain before them; and apart, he wept very plentifully. And after ſome few ſtrange intervening Paſſages, in this 45th Chapter, at laſt dawned, after all this Night of Myſteries, the bright and pleaſant Day; he could not refrain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, nay he wept aloud: He ſaid unto them, v. 3. <hi>I am</hi> Joſeph; <hi>doth my Father yet live? and his brethren could not anſwer, for they were troubled at his preſence.</hi> And in v. 4. he ſaid again, <hi>I am</hi> Joſeph <hi>your brother whom ye ſold into</hi> Egypt. Well they might be aſtoniſhed and afraid, when they knew it was the very <hi>Joſeph</hi> that they envied, and that they ſold: He comforts them againſt exceſſive Grief, telling them, They deſigned Ill,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49606:15"/>but God had a very gracious Deſign in ſuffering all this to come to paſs, and very humbly owns, that <hi>God</hi> ſent him into <hi>Egypt,</hi> v. 8. Then it was he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired them to acquaint his Father with all his Glory: And becauſe it was a very ſurpriſing thing to them, ſo great that they could ſcarcely believe it, he is forced to ſay, v. 12. <hi>Behold your eyes ſee, and the eyes of my brother</hi> Benjamin, <hi>that it is my mouth that ſpeaketh to you.</hi> And v. 14. <hi>He fell upon his brother</hi> Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin<hi>'s neck and wept; and</hi> Benjamin <hi>wept upon his Neck;</hi> their very Souls melted over one another, there were between them the deareſt Tranſports of Love and Joy; there was an Extaſie, or a pleaſant Contact of two Souls run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing each into other: He gives them Waggons to bring down to <hi>Egypt</hi> the reſt of the Family; aſſures them they ſhould have the Fat, and the beſt of the Land; and that they needed not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard their Stuff, <hi>i. e.</hi> to bring their Mean or Ordinary Goods along with them; for all that was Delicate, and Rich, and Pleaſant, was to be theirs.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49606:15"/>And v. 24. he ſent his Brethren away, and they departed, and he ſaid unto them, <hi>See that ye fall not out by the way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Propoſition that I intend to inſiſt upon from theſe Words, ſuitably to the Meaning of our Friend, is this,</p>
            <q>That all good People, <hi>of all Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> ought to agree together.</q>
            <p>I hope my Work at this Time will be to be a <hi>Peace maker;</hi> and ſuch a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, as this of Union, and Love, and Mutual Concord, is of all others moſt delightful to <hi>me,</hi> and I pray God it may be Profitable to us all. I will endeavour to Reconcile all Chriſtians, but I will Reflect upon none that I judge to be truly ſo; I come not to ſhoot Arrows, but to bring Balſom; not to open Wounds, but, as far as I can, to cloſe them up; and may that bleſſed Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that has at this Time called me to ſo excellent a Task, aſſiſt me in it; and if any Perſons came hither Wolves or Tygers, may they go Lambs away;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49606:16"/>if any came hither with Revenge and Paſſion, and Hatred or Prejudices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any good People, may they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, for the Time to come, entertain ſuch a Savage and Brutal Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Good People ſhould not Fall out by the Way or Diſagree, becauſe they have all the ſame Father,</hi> and he is the <hi>God of Peace:</hi> It is uncomely for Children, that have a Father, who ſincerely loves them all, to wrangle and contend with one another: It is unſuitable to their Relation, and reproachful to the Family. 'Tis unnatural for Brethren to fight with one another, <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.8. <hi>And</hi> Abraham <hi>ſaid unto</hi> Lot, <hi>Let there be no ſtrife, I pray thee, between me and thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for we are Brethren.</hi> All Mankind ought to agree together, as having a Participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame Human Nature; they are all Brethren in a larger Senſe, and Sons of the ſame Father <hi>Adam.</hi> Much more ought they ſo to do, who are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from above, the Place of Love and Peace; that are not only of the ſame Nation, but of the ſame Church, that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49606:16"/>is, <hi>the Church of Chriſt;</hi> for you ſhall find me, through this whole Diſcourſe, not to confine my ſelf to this or that Party, but to take in all whom I believe to be ſincerely good.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Good People, of all Denominations, ſhould now agree together, becauſe they have been in Common Danger. Joſeph</hi>'s Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren had like to have ſtarved together, and therefore their Plenty ſhould not make them diſagree. We in this Nation have not felt ſuch a Famine as they did, but we have ſeen heretofore Dangers that threatned us with a Worſe, even a Famine of Hearing the Words of the Lord; and if the <hi>Papiſts</hi> had proſpered in their Plots, Plots that were levelled both againſt <hi>the Church of</hi> England <hi>and Diſſenters,</hi> we had all by this Time been in Common Darkneſs, deſtitute of all Light but that of Fire and Faggot, and then the good of all ſides muſt have agreed to Burn together, though they did not live very quietly together; the Stake would have united thoſe, whom the <hi>Pulpit or the Preſs</hi> could not: They would have ſwallowed us up all; and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49606:17"/>ſhall we not learn ſo much Wiſdom as not to quarrel with one another, which is Sport to them and a Miſchief to us? The World, the Debauch'd, the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Part of Men hate all good People on every ſide, and therefore they ſhould not Hate nor Fall out with one another, remembring how they had like to have periſhed all together, <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.7.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Good People ſhould not quarrel with one another, nor be injurious,</hi> when God has forgiven them all: For <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren to Fall out by the Way, when they were ſo lately pardoned after an heinous and aggravated Crime would have been a very ſhameful thing, and would have made all their future Sin more ſinful: Have not we provoked God more than any of our Friends or Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours can provoke us? He forgives us all thouſands of Sins, and alas we can hardly put up one Injury. It is unbecoming for us now to quarrel, when God is willing to be at Peace with us all, after innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Tranſgreſſions which we have been guilty of. That Man that is of a Wrangling Contentious Humor, is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49606:17"/>either yet in Sin, or has obtained a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for it; if he have his Guilt and Filth upon him, he has much more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Work to do, even to ſearch his Heart and abhor himſelf, and to dwell at Home, inſtead of medling with other Perſons; and if God hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given him, he has very low Thoughts of that Grace, which all the Saints wonder at, when he cannot eaſily forgive his Neighbours Wrongs: Take this for a certain Truth, That <hi>the ſtrongeſt and the beſt Chriſtians are moſt Mild and Gentle;</hi> they are weak and Children in Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that are Paſſionate and Waſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, and Boiſterous and Fretful, for ſo far they are <hi>Carnal, and walk as Men:</hi> And 'tis directly contrary to the Apoſtle's Exhortation, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.31, 32. <hi>Let all bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs and Wrath, and Anger, and Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and Evil-ſpeaking, be put away from you, with all Malice; and be ye kind one to another, forgiving one another even as God for Chriſt's ſake hath forgiven you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If God were not more tender to us all than we are to one another, alas! who could then be ſaved?</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49606:18"/>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>No Good People ſhould fall out by the Way, becauſe they are all Travelling to the ſame bleſſed Home;</hi> they are Strangers and Pilgrims here on Earth, and ſhould as Foreigners and Countrymen that meet in ſome diſtant Land, embrace and be glad to ſee one another. Travellers of ſeveral Nations, <hi>German, Engliſh, Scotch</hi> or <hi>French,</hi> will agree and be civil to one another upon the Road, how different ſoever their Opinions and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions are. We are all travelling to the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and hope all to meet in the ſame Place; and therefore it is highly unſuitable for us to <hi>Fall out by the Way.</hi> Nor will our common Father be pleaſed with us, when we diſagree; we have all the ſame Rule and the ſame Guide, the ſame Leader and the ſame Proſpect of Reward; and therefore we ſhould go Hand in Hand, and hearten and quicken, and encourage one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>Our common Enemies agree together; the Devil, the World, and the Fleſh,</hi> will oppoſe to us their united Srength; our Diviſions do raiſe their Courage, but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49606:18"/>our hearty Love will defeat all their Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems. Our Adverſaries ſow the Seeds of Diſcord, but our Buſineſs is to prevent their after-growth, and not to let the Tares ſpring up, whilſt we are aſleep. Quarrelling among Chriſtians is as fooliſh as if a <hi>Caravan of Merchants,</hi> that travel through the Deſerts, ſhould all fall upon one another, and let the Wild <hi>Arabians,</hi> in the mean while, make a Prey of their Common Stock. Let not the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſharpen their Swords a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one another, whilſt the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> deſign the Ruin of them all.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>Not to fall out by the Way, will make the Way leſs Tedious and more Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant.</hi> 'Tis ſo troubleſome a thing to be always Quarrelling and Contending, that I wonder Men will not be ſo wiſe as to <hi>love their own Quiet.</hi> They are of a very hot Conſtitution whoſe Element is Fire, and who cannot live but in the midſt of Flames. Perſons that are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Fighting, cannot Travel very faſt, it retards their Progreſs, and makes them advance very ſlowly to their Home. In the ordinary Affairs of Life,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49606:19"/>Wrangling hinders all Diſpatch, and no buſineſs is rightly done till Mens Thoughts are cool and Sober. Paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate People uſually make a great Noiſe and Buſtle, but they do but little Work; a Ship does not ſail ſo directly and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Port, in the midſt of Storms, as ſhe does in the more quiet and fairer Calm. <hi>Solomon</hi> very wiſely ſays, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.9. <hi>It is better to dwell in the corner of the houſe top, than with a brawling wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in a wide houſe,</hi> becauſe the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of her Voice will diſturb him in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Place, and effectually with her Clamors hinder all his Buſineſs. 'Tis much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to live in a ſmoaky Cottage, with one of a meek and quiet Spirit, than to live in a Palace with a Scold; the Thunder and the Lightning are not more diſturbing and frightful than ſuch a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Tongue: But now, to live with Holy, Silent, Agreeing People, makes a Man's Houſe his Delight, and his Hours with ſuch happy Society ſlide away with Pleaſure. When they all think and ſpeak the ſame Things, and when their Deſigns and Intereſts, and Hopes
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49606:19"/>are the ſame. Love makes every thing ſweet and eaſie; it makes us yielding and compaſſionate; it makes us prone to Civilities and Kindneſſes, and to all the good Offices we can for others; it makes us to give them good Advice to raiſe them up when they fall, and when they wander to bring them into the right way again. Men that love Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention are uſually ſcorched and pained with the Fires of their own kindling; and 'tis very fit it ſhould be ſo. 'Tis a moſt grievous tireſome thing to a Man of a Quiet Soul, to ſee others always in a Ferment and Vexation, and Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves, when they have none to Reproach; and Poyſoning themſelves with Fury and Paſſion, when they have not ſit Objects whereon to ſpend their Venom.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. <hi>Good People ought not to fall out by the Way, becauſe this will promote their common Strength and Safety.</hi> The Church united is as <hi>an Army with Banners;</hi> her joynt Prayers and Praiſes are formid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to her Enemies: But when ſhe is divided ſhe is liable to be Attacqued
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49606:20"/>and moleſted on every ſide. 'Tis among Chriſtians, as ſome obſerve, it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Roman Armies,</hi> ſo long as they were well united, that their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders held a perfect Underſtanding among themſelves, and their Soldiers were kept in a true Obedience to their Orders, other Nations endeavoured to procure their Friendſhip with great ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſs; they eſteemed it a Glory to enter into Alliance with this People: But ſo ſoon as they diſunited among themſelves, other States deſpiſed their Alliance, and took up Arms againſt them. Whilſt Brethren fall not out by the way, they can aſſiſt and help one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a common Danger; they can ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe and warn, and pray for one another; but when they are divided, that Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, like a preternatural hectical Heat in the Body, makes the Spirits more feeble, and cauſes all its Strength and Beauty to decay. All Societies of Men are both more Illuſtrious and Powerful when they are linked together in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Bond of Love: But our Saviour has told us, <hi>Matt.</hi> 12.25. <hi>Every King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49606:20"/>divided againſt it ſelf is brought to deſolation: And every City or Houſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt it ſelf ſhall not ſtand.</hi> It is therefore the Policy of the Devil, and of Wicked Men, to render good Chriſtians odious to one another, and to engage them in Wranglings and Diſputes, and Quarrels that ſo the Glory of Religion may not be diſcerned when 'tis covered with ſo black a Veil. The whole Courſe of Nature ſubſiſts by the common Union of all its Parts. The Heavens above us, as one obſerves,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Daillee Quinze</hi> Sermons, p. 129.</note> have for many Ages rouled about with an admirable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. The Spheres, in the midſt of many Motions, do not diſturb nor hinder one another; the Stars, both the Wandring and Fixt, conſpire to promote the Good and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Univerſe: The Elements ſweetly communicate among themſelves the Qualities they receive from Heaven: The Air gives to the Earth of its Light, its Winds and its Rains: The Sea gives to the Air of its Vapors and Exalations, and both together give to Plants and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49606:21"/>Living Creatures what is neceſſary for their Nouriſhment and Refreſhment: So the Seaſons of the Year give Place to one another, the Winter to the Spring, and the Spring to the Summer, and the Summer to Autumn, and that to Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter again; and ſo there is a perpetual following of Day and Night, of Light and Darkneſs, of Calm and Storm, of Hot and Cold, of Rain and Shine: In this pleaſant Commerce of the ſeveral Parts of the World does conſiſt its Strength and Beauty; and if it were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted, there would be nothing but Confuſion and Deformity. Union and Agreement is, as he calls it elſwhere, the Soul of the Univerſe, the Ornament of Heaven and Earth, the Life and the Joy of both Worlds.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. <hi>Falling out by the Way, deſtroys the Power of Religion.</hi> It is not much Talking, but a lively Practice of our known Duties, that is the beſt Evidence of our being Chriſtians indeed. If we diſputed leſs and prayed more, if we could but Love and not Quarrel, we ſhould be far better Men: Wrangling
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49606:21"/>may fill our Heads with Notions, but never will enrich our Hearts with Grace; it may enlarge our Knowledge but not promote our Holineſs: It takes up that Warmth and Zeal, and Time and Strength which ſhould be ſpent about our own Salvation, and the Good of others; for a Man that is heated with Paſſion is not fit for Duty; it is not ſuitable to one ſcorched with ſuch a profane Flame, to addreſs himſelf to the God of Peace.
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.7.</note> This <hi>Falling out by the Way</hi> breeds Pride and Envy, and Self-conceit, inſtead of Self-denial and Humility, and Love, and many other ſuch excellent and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Graces. A Polite Writer has well obſerved, That, that Peſtilential Spirit of Diviſion, that Heat of Diſputation, which has for ſo many poſſeſſed Ages and waſted the Catholick Church, and by an unhappy kind of Magick transformed the Zeal of Chriſtian Practice into an Itch of Unchriſtian Diſpute, made the Queſtions about our Creed more nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous than the Letters of it, and by this the Serpent, got into the Paradiſe of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49606:22"/>Chriſt. <hi>Cauſes of the decay of Chriſtian Piety,</hi> p 247.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. <hi>To live in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Concord and Friendſhip, is the State of Heaven:</hi> For that is a calm and quiet State, as well as Pure and Holy. There is the God of Peace; there the Angels and bleſſed Spirits live in perfect Concord with one another; there is no jarring in their mutual Praiſes and Hallelujahs; there are no Axes or Hammers to be heard in that Eternal Temple; that Land is full of the moſt chearful Light and Peace; and we ſhould be ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous while we are below, to be like them above; for as one has well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt it,
<q>
                  <l>All we know of what they do above,</l>
                  <l>Is that they Praiſe and that they Love.</l>
               </q> Do but ſuppoſe a Family, where every part of it is agreed, no bitter Words, no Strife, but a pleaſant ſincere good Will to one another, and every thing is done in Love; and there they live as if they were in Heaven. Suppoſe the People
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49606:22"/>of <hi>London</hi> were all agreed, and had all one common Intereſt, and all ſtudyed and contrived to lay aſide their Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels and Contentions, and Names and Reproaches, and loved as Friends and Neighbours, and Fellow-Citizens; not injuring, not reviling, not undermine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another: Oh what a bleſſed Place would this be, it would be like the New <hi>Jeruſalem!</hi> If all this Nation were agreed, if all the Churches and Kingdoms of the World, did but live in Peace and Friendſhip with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, oh what an Heaven on Earth might we then ſee! And why ſhould not all endeavour in their ſeveral Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that it may be ſo? All good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hope to meet above, and why ſhould they fall out by the Way as they are going thither? All their Enmities will ceaſe there, and why ſhould they not now be Friends? Why ſhould they that hope to live in one and the ſame Glory, now revile or reflect upon one another? All their differences will be compoſed when they arrive there, and why ſhould they now differ? There <hi>Luther</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49606:23"/>and <hi>Calvin,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> will be of all one Mind, there will be no Miſunderſtanding of one another there. Now to live in Strife and Bitterneſs and Wrath is a ſad reſemblance of Hell, for that is a place of univerſal and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Diſcontent and Rage; there is no Peace nor Quiet there for ever; there the guilty condemned Souls, are always accuſing and upbraiding and curſing one another; there they rage againſt God, againſt themſelves, and againſt all the Inſtruments of their Ruin and Calamity.</p>
            <p>Inf. 1. <hi>How unſuitable is it for any under the name of Chriſtian to perſecute others, or to force them to be of their Mind!</hi> 'Tis Barbarous and Inhuman and Antichriſtian, to uſe violence in the Matters of Religion, it is not civil nor like Men ſo to do: How unreaſonable would it appear to be, if you met with ſuch upon the Road, that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to Beat and Rob and Plunder, all that would not ſay as they ſay, nor travail their Pace? It would alſo be an unjuſt Method, a thing that would car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49606:23"/>with it a brand of Eternal Shame, for any Men to injure their Brethren in their Goods, or Lives, or Eſtates, meerly for matters of Opinion, which are Innocent and Harmleſs, and no ways dangerous to the Civil Government. To perſuade gently and with mildneſs is the way to convince a Man if he be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, but Fines and Impriſonments, and harſh Uſage and bad Language, will never make any Mortal think that ſuch as uſe them are in the right way; 'tis a poor Cauſe that is forced to ſerve it ſelf of ſuch inhuman and ſorry Methods; to force Men to believe, is a <hi>French way</hi> indeed, but never was nor never will be Apoſtolical: It ſavours of Hell to be violent and cruel, and our Saviour never intended that Men ſhould be <hi>Dragooned</hi> into Religion, but by all the mild and gentle ways in the World, be perſwaded to receive it. A <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Spirit</hi> wherever it is, is a piece of Popery: 'Tis the proper Character of the Romiſh Church to be fierce and bloody; their Scarlet is dyed with the Blood of the Saints of God. I have
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49606:24"/>learned (ſays the famous Mr. <hi>Chilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth, that great Ornament and Defender of the Proteſtante</hi>) from the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that nothing is more againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, than to force Religion: And of St. <hi>Paul, The Weapons of the Chriſtian Warfare are not Carnal.</hi> And great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for Human Violence may make Men counterfeit, but cannot make them believe; and is therefore fit for nothing but to be breed Form without, and Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm within: Beſides, what will follow from this Method but the preſervation peradventure of Unity, but peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only of Uniformity in particular States and Churches; but the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talizing the greater and more lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diviſions of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and the World? And therefore what can fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low from it, but perhaps in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Carnal Policy, the temporal Benefit and Tranquility of temporal States and Kingdoms, but the infinite prejudice, if not the deſolation of the Kingdom of Chriſt? <hi>Chillingworth</hi>'s Religion of Proteſtants, <hi>Sect. I. Ch. V. p.</hi> 228. <hi>Ed.</hi> 5.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49606:24"/>
            <p>Inf. 2. <hi>How Beautiful are the feet of them that Preach the Goſpel of Peace,</hi> Rom. 10.15. They deſerve a free and chearful Entertainment that Preach this Goſpel of Peace in a <hi>peaceable and quiet</hi> manner, when they do not mingle their own Paſſions with the Truths of God, and carry that Heat and Bitterneſs into the Sanctuary, which would be diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed about any common things. The Miniſters of Chriſt are honourable, both with reſpect to their Character, and the Meſſage that they are charged with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, that is, to perſuade Men to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God, and then to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and they have this further advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage too, that they may as they ought frequently inſtil into the Minds of their Hearers, the neceſſity of Peace and Quietneſs and Friendſhip, and how amiable it is ſelf, and how ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God ſuch a Temper is. It is the work of a Miniſter to be <hi>an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of Breaches,</hi> to reſolve the Doubtful, and to compoſe Quarrels as ſoon as ever they begin to riſe; as well knowing that no Churches ever thrive, where
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49606:25"/>Love and Brotherly Kindneſs do not abound. But they are very unhappy Men who are never pleaſed but with Invective, who firſt kindle Fires in their own Breaſts, and chafe their own Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits with eager and ſevere Thoughts of thoſe whom they account their Enemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and then warm their Sermons with this Terreſtrial culinary Fire; and ſo I call it, becauſe that Heat and that Light which comes from Heaven, is pure and peaceable, and ſoft and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; that Doctrin will certainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the beſt effect which drops as the Due, its mild Influences will both pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and Delight. A Miniſter of all Men in the World, ſhould be Meek and Compaſſionate and Loving to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for he is an Ambaſſadour from the Prince of Peace: His Sermons, his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits, his Inſtructions, his every Action ſhould tend to promote this; and upon all occaſions to ſhew the evil of Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring and Reviling and Backbiting, and a thouſand other too common Sins, that have very much of the Image of the Devil in them, as they are Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49606:25"/>Wickedneſſes, and they are always highly diſgraceful to Religion. Woful were thoſe times, and unſuitable to their character were thoſe Men, that would turn their Sermons into ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Satyrs and Alarms, their Pulpits into Drums, and their Congregations into a Field of Battle: Unhappy were the times, when the Preacher was moſt <hi>hummed</hi> when he was moſt full of <hi>Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery,</hi> and that was thought the beſt and moſt witty Sermon that was the moſt ſharp: Such Perſons ſpoke not as if their Tongues were touched with a Coal from the Altar, but as if they had been ſcorched with Fire from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. God forgive thoſe Men that ſought by all manner of Reviling Speeches, to render their Brethren odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Magiſtrates and the common People, and as far as they could, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate both againſt them; and may a peculiar Bleſſing be on their Heads, who are now <hi>of the higheſt Rank in the Church,</hi> and who were then, to their Immortal Honour be it ſpoken, <hi>Men of great Calmneſs, Temper</hi> and <hi>Moderation;</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:49606:26"/>of ſuch no Church will ever have cauſe to be aſhamed, though ſhe may bluſh for thoſe who were then <hi>Sons of Coal,</hi> and who increaſed the Flames they ſhould have quenched. Above all things a Miniſter muſt be apt to forgive private Injuries, and not to quarrel with his Hearers for ſmall matters nor on every ſlight occaſion; for this will unavoidably prejudice them againſt his Doctrin, and render it altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsful: And if they be of my mind, they'll not care to hear a paſſionate and froward Man; for I think, he has nothing in him attractive, whoſe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Gift lyes in railing at others, and who by that provocation are frequently tempted to rail at him again; and <hi>thus they fall out by the Way,</hi> when they might with great eaſe Travel lovingly together.</p>
            <p>Inf. 3. <hi>See hence the woful Effects of</hi> Adam<hi>'s Fall:</hi> This occaſioned all the Diſorders that are both in the great and little World, all the Storms and Huri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, and Tempeſts and Inundations, and Miſeries that break the Peace of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49606:26"/>Creation, and all thoſe unbecoming violent Paſſions, that are in the minds of Men; who are now like the Beaſts that periſh, and as ſo many Wolves and Lyons to one another. Surely nothing of this would have ever hapned, had not our firſt Parents taſted of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Fruit. By Tranſgreſſing the Command of God, the Harmony of the lower World was greatly ſpoiled, and Confuſion, and War, and Bloodſhed, came inſtead of Peace and Love, from that time to this; theſe two happy Gueſts have been Strangers to the Sons of Men. To be Paſſionate and Reveng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Quarrelſome, is to have the old Man in his Strength; but to be Meek, and Humble, and Lowly and Forgiving, is to be conformable to the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> 'tis to ſhine with his Image, who came to repair the breaches of the Fall; therefore, ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.7, 8. <hi>Now you alſo put off all theſe, Anger, Wrath, Malice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Inf.</hi> 4. The great Patience of God that ſo bears with all his Children, when they fall out by the way, and cannot
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49606:27"/>bear with one another; it is their Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, their Folly, and their Sin ſo to do; but for <hi>his own ſake,</hi> though he is fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpleaſed at it, yet he lets not all his Anger burſt out upon them: Would it not move even a mild and gentle Father, to ſee his Children always quarrelling, when he provides for them all? Their Strife and Bitterneſs does vex his Soul, but he remembers they are his Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren ſtill; and they are but Children; and he knows when they have grown to riper and wiſer years, even for their own eaſe they will be more quiet. Alas! they are <hi>Children in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> that are Peeviſh and Fretful and ſoon Angry; and when their Minds are more Enlightned, they will by degrees be like their Heavenly Father, who is Merciful and Kind <hi>and ſlow to Wrath,</hi> Pſal. 103.8, 9. It ſhould fill us with wonder to conſider how gracious, how compaſſionate, and how good our God is to us all, when we are many times full of Bitterneſs and Venom againſt one another.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:49606:27"/>
            <p>The next Thing is to enquire whence it is that good People and Brethren are apt to fall out by the way: The cauſes of it are ſuch as theſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ariſes from their Luſts and the remaining Corruption of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.9. All the Commotions that diſturb the Peace of the World or of the Church, have their Original from the inward depraved Habits of the Souls of Men: None are ſatisfied with their own Stations, ſome ſeek to climb higher than they are, and ſo juſtle and quarrel with all that oppoſe their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious deſigns; ſome have an inward grudging at the Reputation and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Serviceableneſs of others, and their envy kindles a Rage within their Breaſts, which may be ſtifled by pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Conſiderations for a while; but it is ſo tormenting, that it vents it ſelf either in Reproaches or Oppoſition, or Contempt of others, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.26. And Covetouſneſs, and an immoderate De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Wealth, is the occaſion of many fold Contentions; and indeed it is for Mony or Dominion, or ſome ſuch al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49606:28"/>Bait, that the greateſt part of the World quarrel with one another; or ſome Intereſt they have, that is the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol of their Hearts, which they love, and which they are afraid they muſt part withal, if they ſhould agree. Too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Men, in the Matters of Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult more their Temporal Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage than God's Glory; and it has been often obſerved by Learned Men,
<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Reynold</hi>'s Works. p. 949.</note> That Avarice and Ambition, a Spirit of Contention, a corrupt Conſcience and Carnal Ends have uſually been the Original of thoſe Hereſies which have from Time to Time annoyed the Church of God; and that <hi>Arius, Valentinus, Marcian, Montanus, Novatus</hi> and others, by their Ambition and Impatience of Repulſe, revolted from the Truth. Thus the Diſciples ſtrove together on the Way, and it was who ſhould be greateſt: To be Great in the World is that which many Perſons ſo vehemently deſire, that to attain it they ſcruple not to diſturb their own, their Neighbours, and the common Peace. It is from Guilt, and the too
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49606:28"/>great Power of Sin in Brethren, <hi>that they fall out by the Way. Joſeph</hi> gave this Caution to his Brethren, becauſe they had accuſed themſelves, as being verily guilty of great Barbarouſneſs and Cruelty towards him, and he was afraid that they might too ſeverely reproach one another upon that account.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>This falling out often proceeds from a croſs-grain'd Temper:</hi> A little good Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Religion would bring the World and the Church to a ſtate of Peace; but ſome People are of ſo <hi>ſowre</hi> and <hi>moroſe a Conſtitution,</hi> that nothing that others do, pleaſes them, and ſo they fall out with them: Some are ſo touchy and crabbed, that the leaſt thing puts them into a Flame, the leaſt Moleſtation gives them an occaſion of ſtinging and troubling them: Some are ſo Peeviſh that the leaſt miſunderſtood Word or Expreſſion that they do not like, puts them all into a Heat. I generally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, That <hi>Good-natur'd People,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Conformiſts</hi> or <hi>Nonconformiſts, do moſt eaſily and pleaſantly agree together:</hi> And that thoſe that are under the Curſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49606:29"/>of an uneaſie rugged Temper, never do, nor will agree. I am ſure there would be a great deal of more Peace in the World, if Men would but ſtrive to reſiſt the <hi>Vices of their own Conſtitution;</hi> I am ſure they would be leſs Wranglers if they were more <hi>Gentlemen;</hi> for it is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſagreeable to a well-bred Man, to be always contradicting and oppoſing others; a ſweet, affable, courteous, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging Carriage and Expreſſion, does inſenſibly draw one to a good Opinion of thoſe among whom it is obſerved; and a ſtiff inflexible Temper, is a vaſt hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to the Beauty and the Progreſs of Religion: There may be good People that are bad natur'd; but then, I ſay, it is their Duty to ſtrive againſt, and not to indulge their own Weakneſs. Some Men are naturally hot and fiery, and eager, and violent, and it is their Duty to cool this Heat with very ſerious and deliberate Conſideration, leſt it ruin themſelves, at laſt as it now vexes others. It is a moſt honourable thing for any Perſon to be yielding and full of Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion towards others in all Lawful and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49606:29"/>Neceſſary Things. I ſhould reckon it a very great Miſery as could well befal a Man of Temper, of Meekneſs and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to be bound always to live with a moroſe crabbed Man; it would be a very ſevere and tormenting Puniſhment. Some are naturally boiſterous and ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and full of that Clamour which the Apoſtle reproves, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.31, 32. and ſuch diſturb the World, which if they could learn Silence, would quickly be at Eaſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>This falling out by the Way, among good People, proceeds from want of frequent Converſation and Acquaintance with one another.</hi> They whet their Spirits with abundance of <hi>uſeleſs and dry Diſputes,</hi> and when they come affably and civilly to talk together, they find they are all of one Mind. Strangeneſs and Diſtance, and reſervedneſs and ſhyneſs, perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate many times the Quarrels and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions which an Hour or two's fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Diſcourſe would remove. Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance among. Men of different Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will by degrees cauſe them to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a better and more favourable Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49606:30"/>of each other than they had before; and indeed, as one very well obſerves, we ought to converſe with one another as Friends, and remember, that the way to Agreement of all Parties is not to bring Men to be of one Opinion, but to be of one Mind; which we may be, though of different Opinions: Not by thinking the ſame things, but by think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well one of another; endeavouring to preſerve Charity as carefully as to preſerve Truth (<hi>Biſhop</hi> Patrick's <hi>ſecond Part of a Sermon before the then Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>p.</hi> 39.) I do not ſee any Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why a <hi>Conformiſt</hi> ſhould ſhun our Society, or we theirs; nor why we ſhould be ſtrange to one another, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have not the very ſame Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in <hi>things that are not Eſſential to Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Liſtning to Backbiters is another Cauſe of falling out.</hi> Some People have ſo <hi>little Religion and ſo little Buſineſs,</hi> that they can find nothing to do but to gad about to tell Stories of this or that Perſon, whom they or their Friend does not like; And if they be regarded, ſuch
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49606:30"/>Buſie-Bodies will occaſion abundance of Strife. It is a wiſe Man's Part to ſtiffle all their Revilings, or not to give any Credit to them, for Tale Bearers are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the moſt Credulous and the moſt Impertinent, and the moſt Cenſorious, and the moſt Noiſy of any People in the World; they will always commend themſelves, and always reflect on others. And it is a Sign they know not their own Hearts, when they meddle ſo much with others; I am afraid they <hi>keep not their own Vineyard,</hi> nor ſweep their own Houſe, they are ſo very much abroad; and the hearkening to ſuch ſilly People does oftentimes breed a laſting Miſchief. It would cauſe us to have an ill Opinion of Many that are a great deal better than they are repreſented, and to ſow Diſcord among Brethren, is one of the <hi>ſeven things that are an Abomination to the Lord,</hi> Prov. 6.18. Some Men take Delight to ſet others a quarrelling toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and it is Muſick to them to behold the Flames which they have kindled. Tale-bearers are a ſort of Hawkers and Pedlers of groundleſs Reports, which
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49606:31"/>they take in the Groſs, and afterwards Retail out in all Companies, and it ought to be the Care of every good Man to have them ſuppreſs'd, for they great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hinder the Progreſs of Love.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Another Cauſe why Men fall out is, becauſe they are very proud of their own Apprehenſions, and cannot bear to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted.</hi> They would be humoured, and have all People to ſay juſt as they ſay, or to think as they think: <hi>Self-will and Self conceit are the greateſt undermin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Peace and Quietneſs both in Churches and Families.</hi> You meet with abundance of People that cannot bear to have their Wills croſt in the leaſt, or to have their Opinions examined and brought to the Teſt; they carry it ſo haughtily as if they only were Infallible, and all others were in the dark; ſome Undervalue others becauſe they have not their Parts and Learning, or becauſe they will not blindly ſubmit to their Dictates, and ſubſcribe every thing which they ſay is True: And others, though they want Learning, yet have great Confidence, and will not ſuffer any to be in the Right
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49606:31"/>but who uſe <hi>their Terms,</hi> and juſt <hi>their way of Expreſſion:</hi> It is better to be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable than to be only Learned: And 'tis better to be humble than to be too well conceited of our own Abilities; <hi>a proud Man is a very bad Neighbour;</hi> to dwell with ſuch an one is to dwell with Storms and Tempeſts, with Waves and Rocks, for if he be Proud he is hard to pleaſe, and can never be a good Friend. Men are generally fond of the Brats of their own Brain, and are very angry if others that ſee no Cauſe for it, will not doat as much upon them as they do, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.10. the Pride of many is ſo great, that they cannot live in any quiet unleſs they be flattered, and unleſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will acquieſce in all their Actions, &amp; ſuffer themſelves to be trod upon. And Self conceited Men,
<note place="margin">Sir <hi>William Temple</hi>'s Obſ. on the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> p. 169.</note> as one ſays, talk much of right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and mean always their own; and make their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Imagination the meaſure of general Truth; and the Diſpute between them and us, ends at laſt in three Words, which it might as well have ended in at
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49606:32"/>firſt, That they are in the Right, and we are in the Wrong.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Another occaſion of falling out is from an Ignorance of Human Nature:</hi> It is ſtrange, Men do not conſider that as there is a <hi>variety of Souls,</hi> there always is and will be ſome <hi>variety of Thoughts;</hi> ſome men have a quicker ſight than others, and penetrate with great eaſe and pleaſure into the deepeſt receſs of Truth, whither a Man of a duller capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city will never come. It would be a very ſenſeleſs thing for one to be angry with another, that he cannot ſee ſo well nor at ſo great a diſtance as he can. All Perſons will never have the very ſame Gifts nor the ſame Degrees of Grace, and upon this account there will be different Apprehenſions, though they ought for all that to bear with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for whilſt they are in this World they will but <hi>know in part,</hi> and but little of what is ſtill further to be known. And one great Reaſon of the various Sentiments of Perſons about one and the ſame thing, is from the Contexture of their Spirits; in ſome they are very
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49606:32"/>pure and lively, in others they are groſs and more terreſtrial; and according to theſe they have either a finer and more ſprightly, or a more dull and leſs active Soul, which will act whilſt it is in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in very many things conformable to the good or ill Humours of the Body, where it lodges during its Abſence from the ſpiritual and unſeen World. And Men frequently mingle their particular Inclinations (to which they are led by their Conſtitution, and which they greatly value) with the Matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Thus take (as one obſerves) a Man greatly admiring natural Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, he will be apt to mingle and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie Religion with Philoſophical Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Behmen</hi> who was a great Chymiſt, reſolves almoſt all Religion into Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtry, and frames his Conceptions of Religion ſuitable and conformable to Chymical Notions. Many great Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians that have much obſerved the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Man's Body, have figured to themſelves Notions of the Soul con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to their Obſervations in the Body: And ſo again, Men of Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49606:33"/>and Notional Brains have conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion, and their Notions of it to Metaphyſicks, and indeed have made that which is, and ought to be the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Principle for the actuating of all Men, yea even of the meaneſt Capacities, to be a meer Collection of Subtilties far more abſtruſe than the moſt intricate and ſublimated Learning whatſoever. <hi>See the L. Ch. Juſt.</hi> Hale<hi>'s Diſc. of Rel. p.</hi> 26. Beſides, Parents, and Examples, and Education, and Company, and Books have their ſeveral Influences upon the Thoughts of Men; and it is unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to expect <hi>an entire <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> among thoſe whoſe early Years have been ſeaſoned with Principles and Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions very different from one another; and we ought to make great Allowances to one another upon this Account.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Another Cauſe of Brethen's falling out by thy way, is when they impoſe things upon their Brethren, that are but in their own Nature Indifferent,</hi> as if they were abſolutely neceſſary; or will not hold Communion with others, unleſs they will agree to all the Terms which they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49606:33"/>have propoſed, as it would be an unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable thing for a Man not to allow me to Travel with him in the ſame Road, unleſs I will wear a Garment of the ſame Colour with his own, and ſtop or go on, juſt as he would have me ſtay or go; and yet for the ſake of Peace, I may comply with him in ſeveral things which I take to be Innocent and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, though I can by no means praiſe him for his enjoyning them. It is no doubt (as one ſays) a very deſirable thing to leſſen the differences of Chriſtians,
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Wake</hi>'s Sermons, p. 282.</note> and enlarge their Communion as far as ever we can; and it has never gone well with the Church of Chriſt, ſince Men have been ſo narrow ſpirited, as to mix the Controverſies of Faith with their publick Forms of Worſhip, and have made their <hi>Liturgies,</hi> inſtead of being Offices of Devotion to God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Teſts and Cenſures of the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Brethren. It is a miſerable thing when Men agree in Fundamentals, and in all thoſe common Truths that are abſolutely neceſſary to be known in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49606:34"/>order to Salvation, that they cannot bear with one another in leſs conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things; and without doubt the beſt things are the plaineſt, and the leaſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable; and unleſs we can prove our ſelves to be Infallible, we cannot claim of others a total Submiſſion to what we ſay or impoſe upon them; and unleſs by the Light of Reaſon and of Scripture, we can gently convince them that they are in the wrong way, and that we are in the right. And if we be in the right and have ſetled things very well, yet if the peace of the Church be like to be injured by their ſcrupling of ſeveral things as ſinful, in the lawfulneſs of which we are very well ſatisfied; yet it will be no' Reproach to us, to make ſuch alterations and abatements in the conditions of our Communion, as may ſhew that we moſt charitably deſire to have them to worſhip God with us, and in our Aſſemblies; for nothing Human can be ſo compleat, as not to need by ſome unforeſeen Circumſtances, ſome Variation. No harm will enſue, ſo long as the things moſt <hi>Fundamental</hi> are
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49606:34"/>agreed on both ſides; and as one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, Charity to a weak Brother in things indifferent in their own nature, is then to be exerciſed when my Brother is offended therewith, or never: And if it be ſaid, it is his Duty to ſubmit to the Church, and not the Church to him, I do think that Anſwer will not ſerve in this Caſe; for ſurely though a Child owes a Duty to a Father, yet his neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect thereof, eſpecially if it be upon a Conſcientious Account, will not excuſe the neglect of a Father's duty to his Child: The Apoſtle profeſſed he would abſtain from things lawful, rather than offend his weak Brother. <hi>See the L. Ch. Juſt.</hi> Hale<hi>'s Diſc. of Relig. p.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Another cauſe of falling out by the way, is from a littleneſs and narrowneſs of Soul;</hi> when Perſons will have no good opinion of any, but ſuch as are of their own Way and Party; when they will cry up their own Men with exceſſive Praiſes, and run down all others with the ſame Breath. Such are like the Jews of whom we have read, that living in ſome remote Place ſurrounded with
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49606:35"/>Seas, becauſe they have no Correſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with others, think that <hi>they</hi> are all the World, and that the Race of Men is confined to ſo ſmall a number. It is a moſt uncomly thing for any Party of Chriſtians, to ſay that none can be ſaved but in their way; as if they did not know, that ſeveral Roads may all lead to the very ſame Place; and ſeveral Apprehenſions about leſs neceſſary things, not hinder their paſſage to the ſame Glory. <hi>Let us take heed leſt we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the Kingdom of our Lord,</hi> and make his Empire leſs extenſive than it is. He hath his People ſcattered up and down the World, and it would be a fooliſh and uncharitable thing, to ſay we alone are the <hi>true Church,</hi> and there is none ſo beſides our ſelves: Let us take heed of ſuch a <hi>littleneſs of Soul,</hi> and of ſuch an ignorance of the State and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of Chriſtianity; let us not judge nor condemn, nor think hardly of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man, becauſe he is not of our way; but ſtop our Cenſures, till we know the Reaſons upon which he differs from us. We need not <hi>Fall out by the Way,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49606:35"/>we cannot all think and ſpeak alike; it would be a rude and uncivil thing for an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> ſuppoſe, to fall out with a <hi>Frenchman</hi> upon a Journey, becauſe his Air, his Addreſs, his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his Prounciation, and the Tone of his Language differs from his own: A Publick and Generous Spirit, will love the Name, the Intereſt of Chriſt, and his Glory, wherever it is advanced, though by Perſons of another Perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or in Places vaſtly diſtant from his own Country. Let us carefully diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between things that are really Momentous, and thoſe that are but Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles: Let us not lay too great a ſtreſs on <hi>the little Things</hi> that are peculiar to this or that Party; for a great many are, as one ſays, like a Company of Boys that blow Bubbles out of a Walnut-ſhell; every one runs after his Bubble, and calls it Religion; and every one meaſures the Religion or Ireligion of another, by their agreeing and differing with them in theſe and the like Matters; and at beſt whilſt we ſcramble about the pieces of the Shell, the Kernel is either loſt,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49606:36"/>or gotten by ſome that do not prize any of their Conteſts. And we ought to conſider (as a great Man obſerves) That Belief is no more in a Man's Power than his Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<note place="margin">Sir <hi>William Temple</hi>'s Obſ. on the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> p. 168.</note> or his Feature; and he that tells me I muſt change my Opinion for his, becauſe 'tis the truer and the better, without other Arguments, that have to me the force of Conviction, may as well tell me, I muſt change my grey Eyes, for others like his, that are black, becauſe theſe are lovelier or more in eſteem.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>The great Cauſe why Brethren fall out by the way, is from the Malice and Policy of the Devil:</hi> It is delightful to God, Angels and Saints, to ſee them live together in Unity; but to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil it is greatly vexatious; for Peace and Love do oppoſe his Deſigns, and render that Religion which he hates, amiable and venerable in the Eyes of all. The Devil fires furious and angry People with more Flame and Heat; this Engineer blows the Coals, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes Strife and Contention; and he
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49606:36"/>knows that if he can make Perſons once very Paſſionate, he thereby unfits them for all due performance of Duty, either to God or Man; they unhinge themſelves, and moleſt others too. There are many People, whom the Devil finds he cannot ruin by groſs carnal Sins, as Theft, and Whoredom, and Swearing, and Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, and Sabbath-breaking and the like; whom he endeavours to deſtroy by ſpiritual Sins, ſuch as Envy and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring, and Bitterneſs, and Wrath, and Malice; for all theſe are moſt agreeable to his own Helliſh Nature, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.26, 27. <hi>Be ye angry and Sin not, let not the Sun go down upon your Wrath; neither give place to the Devil.</hi> To be paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and long angry, is to let the Devil Triumph over you, 'tis to bind your ſelves with Chains, and let him lead you Captive at his will: He once fell from Heaven like Lightning, and he has ever ſince inflamed and diſturbed the World, and has a peculiar Malice againſt the Goſpel; and his great Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is to hinder it from being a Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Peace and Mercy, and ſo to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49606:37"/>render it in a great meaſure unſucceſsful by the Quarrels of thoſe that pretend to obey its Laws: And it is obſervable, That (as one ſays) no Quarrels were raiſed among the Heathens about the ſeveral Gods they worſhipped; for the Devil, the irreconcileable Enemy to God's Glory and Man's Happineſs, was pleaſed with their deadly Errors, and let them adore the Hoſt of Heaven, or of the Earth, it was alike to him, for they all diverted the Minds of Men from the ſole Object of Divine Worſhip, the True God. The Devil makes his Slaves to Fire Towns, and Depopulate Countries, and to Deſtroy Churches, and Diſorder Families: Let us not warm our ſelves at his Fire, nor in the leaſt reſemble his Cruel Nature. Let us all fight againſt him with one accord, remembring we ſerve the Prince of Peace, and <hi>his Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners over us are Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>An Ignorant and Miſguided Zeal:</hi> Or as the Apoſtle calls it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.2. <hi>A Zeal of God,</hi> but not according to Knowledge; and 'tis no wonder if Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons juſtle againſt one another when they
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49606:37"/>are Blind or in the Dark: When they call that Truth which is not ſo, or when they are as violently concerned for their own Opinions as if they were plainly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed; or when they are ſolicitous to preſerve real Truth, but go about it with too much Warmth and Hear, or make too great a Noiſe about it. Zeal muſt be tempered with a great deal of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, if it be truly genuine and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</p>
            <p>The next thing is to ſhew, what Methods may be taken by Perſons of all Perſuaſions, <hi>That they may not fall out by the Way;</hi> and the principal is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To take Care that they believe in Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> He is the Prince of Peace, and all that yeild themſelves to be his Subjects, he brings by degrees to this amiable Frame; a Spirit of Gentleneſs, and Mildneſs is conveyed to all the Parts of the Body, from this peaceable and bleſſed Head. Faith in Chriſt gives us Union with him, and conveys a ſtrength to us, whereby we may ſubdue all our Sins; among which a proneneſs to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49606:38"/>and fall out with one another is not the moſt inconſiderable; <hi>whoever has this Faith is immediately thereupon a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the true Church,</hi> has a Right to all the Sacraments and Ordinances of the Goſpel; and if any ſhould refuſe ſuch a Believer admiſſion into this or that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, they muſt do it at their own Peril: if I had ſo great an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as to have a particular Charge of Souls, all good Chriſtians, under what Names ſoever they go, of <hi>Conformiſts,</hi> or <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> or <hi>Independents,</hi> or <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> I would, upon their Deſire, their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to live peaceably, moſt chearfully receive them into my Communion, and though one ſhould be for Receiving the Lord's Supper <hi>Kneeling, another Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or another Sitting,</hi> I would not think it in the leaſt contrary to Decency or Order to adminiſter it to them all in their diſtinct Poſtures; for if I thought them true Believers, how could I dare to refuſe them, merely becauſe they were not ſatisfied in this or that Geſture, which, it may be, I ſhould think moſt Proper and Convenient: <hi>All good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49606:38"/>are of the ſame Church;</hi> and if our Bleſſed Lord will receive them all into one Heaven at laſt, Wo to them that ſhall refuſe to receive them here; for certainly that which Qualifies a Man for Heaven and Everlaſting Salvation, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifies him for Communion with any Church on Earth whatſoever; for the Principal Enquiry of the great Day will not be of what Party we were, whether <hi>Conformiſts</hi> or <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we really believed in Chriſt, and took him for our Lord and King? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we were of his Body, and renewed by his Spirit, and ſubject to his Laws? The great Rule for Peaceful Agreement among Chriſtians in their ſeveral Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, is that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.5, 6, 7. <hi>Receive ye one another, as Chriſt alſo received us to the glory of God.</hi> And Chriſt <hi>receives us all moſt</hi> kindly when we believe. Our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Faith in him is our higheſt Honour, &amp; that well evidenced gives us the trueſt Right to all Church Communion. I would earneſtly deſire People that are cenſorious and narrow ſould, to read the 14th to the <hi>Romans</hi> often over, as a
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49606:39"/>moſt excellent means to cool their Heats and Animoſities.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That you may not fall out by the way, you muſt not give one another bad Names, nor uſe Provoking Venomous Expreſſions to one another.</hi> How many laſting Quarrels and Contentions ariſe by ſome awkward and ſcurvy Titles that Men give to others, whom by that means they make their Adverſaries? All would be calm and quiet but for ſuch an Evil Tongue as <hi>James</hi> deſcribes ch. 3.6. <hi>The tongue is a Fire, a world of iniquity, it deflleth the whole body, and ſetteth on fire the courſe of nature, and is ſet on fire of Hell.</hi> The Devil and an Evil Tongue go together. Bitter Speeches exaſperate and chaſe thoſe that otherwiſe would be at Eaſe; and it is a great Weakneſs when Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians cannot omit Perſonal Reflections, but love to Satyrize on one another, as if they were in Jeſt, when by their ſharpen'd Animoſities the poor injur'd Church receives many Wounds. O that all our other Names were laid aſide, and only the Name of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> retained among us; then we might ſomewhat
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49606:39"/>reſemble the purer Ages of the Church, when their Buſineſs was to live, nor to talk great Matters; and the Name <hi>Chriſtian</hi> (as one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) did ſo charm them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Horneck<hi>'s Letter to a Perſon of Quality, p.</hi> 490</note> that though there were various Degrees of Men among them, Eccleſiaſticks, Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Virgins, Widows, Married Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Confeſſors, Martyrs and Friends, yet the Name Chriſtian ſwallowed up all; and in this they triumphed beyond all other Titles in the World: Which, as he ſays, made <hi>Attalus</hi> in <hi>Euſebius,</hi> when the Governour asked him, What Countryman he was? who his Father and Mother were? what Trade, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and Employment he was of? whether he was Rich or Poor? give no other Anſwer but this, That he was a Chriſtian. Give to your Neighbours, and to thoſe that in ſome things differ from you, the moſt kind and affable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions: It is an unſeemly thing for Chriſtians to fix ignominious Names upon one another, when one ſide will ſay, <hi>That the other are Formaliſts,</hi> and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49606:40"/>know little of the Power of Godlineſs: And when another Party will ſay, That all that differ from their Ceremonies do but <hi>Cant and Whine, and make a Shew,</hi> and that all their Profeſſion is Hypocriſy: Theſe are both to blame. What Miſchief have we ſeen ſpread in the Minds of Men, under ſeveral new-coyn'd Names, as of <hi>Whig and Tory,</hi> and the like? and formerly a great deal of Trouble was occaſioned by the differing Names of <hi>Presbyterian and Independent:</hi> But now, Thanks be to God, thoſe Names are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and I hope and wiſh that they may never have a Reſurrection, ſeeing we have lately given them a very decent Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral: The Name of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Miniſters</hi> and People, is a thouſand times more Honourable: And <hi>The Heads of Agreement</hi> between theſe two fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Perſuaſions, and the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and learned of either ſide, will, I queſtion not, for many Ages be a Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to us; and bleſſed be that <hi>Day of Peace,</hi> in which they were concluded: Bleſſed be that God of Love that ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to our <hi>Fathers</hi> and our <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:49606:40"/>ſuch peaceable and uniting Reſolutions, which when I my ſelf ſaw concluded, I could not but think that Healing Day to be as <hi>one of the Days of Heaven,</hi> and as a Reſemblance of that Holy Place, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all Good Miniſters and People ſhall agree together; and who could forbear ſaying with <hi>David,</hi> Pſ. 133.1. <hi>Behold how good and how pleaſant it is for brethren to dwell together in unity!</hi> And eſpecially if you would not fall out, be not always ripping up <hi>Old Sores,</hi> nor ſpeaking of things that may kindle Strife, and not allay it, as they did that in a more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Time uſed to be always talking of 41. and of that Rebellion; not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing, That many of themſelves would upon ſome parallel Emergencies uſe the very ſame Arguments, and do ſome of the ſame things. Neither ought we to upbraid others always with the Doctrin of <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> of which I verily believe the more Ingenuous and Learned part of the Clergy are now very much aſhamed; inasmuch as in the way that it was frequently, though moſt unwarily preſſed, it was a very ſlaviſh Doctrin.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:49606:41"/>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That you may not fall out by the Way, put the faireſt Conſtruction that you poſſibly can upon the Carriage and Actions of thoſe that in ſome things differ from you: Take every thing by the beſt Handle, and do not wreſt their Words to a Purpoſe which they never intended.</hi> Do not load them nor their Doctrins with Conſequences which they neither own nor ſee; conſider they are to ſtand or fall to their own Maſter, and not to be judged at your Bar: Oh! take care that you condemn none of thoſe in your Cenſures, whom Chriſt will own and juſtifie at the Great Day. What Peace would be in Families and Churches, and larger Societies, if Men would not ſtretch Words beyond their Natural Signification; nor conceive an abiding Diſguſt from this or that Miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood Expreſſion, with which the Speaker never deſigned to affront them, or which he never levelled at them? They entertain many things which were never ſent them, and ſuch touchy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple plant Bryars in their own Spirits; they never want Vexation, nor never will. See what the Apoſtle ſays of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49606:41"/>Charity. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Charity ſuffereth long and is kind, charity envieth not, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity vaunteth not it ſelf, it is not puft up, doth not behave it ſelf unſeemly, ſeeketh not her own, is not eaſily provoked, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no evil, rejoyceth not in Iniquity, but rejoyceth in truth, beareth all things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth all things, enduring all things.</hi> There are many waſpiſh and angry Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that behave themſelves as if they had never heard of ſuch a <hi>Chapter,</hi> or of ſuch a Grace; I deſire them to read this Deſcription often over, and alſo the firſt Epiſtle of St. <hi>John,</hi> that <hi>Loving Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple;</hi> as alſo to meditate on the Life of Chriſt, with what Meekneſs, with what what Lowlineſs and Affability he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried himſelf to all, unleſs that now and then he was a little ſharp towards the Superſtitious Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Reſiſt the beginnings of Strife and Falling out; for how great a Matter will a little Fire kindle?</hi> Jam. 3.5. a few miſplaced Words many times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a Quarrel, though the Storm ought by Prudence and mutual Forgiveneſs to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49606:42"/>be laid, as ſoon as it begins to riſe. If petty Differences among Men were but compoſed with a ſuitable and an early diligence, how many Law-ſuits, which are both tedious and very coſtly, might be with eaſe prevented? For continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Anger makes thoſe People that are hot, to be more hot, it chafes and fires them more and more: A Diſeaſe taken betimes admits of help or ſome mitigation, which will not yield to all the moſt prudent Methods of Phyſick, that are uſed after it is become ſtrong and obſtinate: Therefore the Wiſe Man adviſes us, <hi>To leave off Contention before it be medled with.</hi> It may ſeem, (as one ſays) a Contradiction to leave it off before it is medled with; but we are ſo early to retire from all Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that as ſoon as it appears, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have engaged in it, we muſt break it off; for if we are once enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, Humour, Honour, and other peeviſh or deſigning Men will hold us to it; therefore it is beſt to break it off in time.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:49606:42"/>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Carry it always towards thoſe that diſſent from you, in a ſweet and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging manner:</hi> Let not their different Opinions make you Moroſe or Froward; be very Civil to thoſe whoſe Perſuaſion is not the ſame with yours: A <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt</hi> ought to do all the good Offices of Kindneſs that he can, for a <hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt;</hi> and the Nonconformiſt the like again to him: I ſee no Reaſon why we ſhould be ſhy or unkind to one another, we are both <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> and we are both of one Religion. Remember that a <hi>Meek and Quiet Spirit is of great Price in the ſight of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.4. and verſ. 8. <hi>Be ye all of one Mind, having Compaſſion one of another: Love as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, be Pitiful, be Courteous, not ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Evil for Evil, or Railing for Railing; but contrary-wiſe Bleſſing, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ye are thereunto called, that you ſhould inherit a Bleſſing.</hi> In the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times they could forbear and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give their Enemies, much more their Brethren; and were not like the Waſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Philoſophers, who, as one ſays,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49606:43"/>were ready to fall foul up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one another,
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Cave</hi>'s Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, pt. 3. ch. 3. p. 317.</note> for every petty and inconſiderable Difference that was among them. Chriſtians, as he ſays, were careful not to offend either God or Man, but to keep and maintain Peace with both; thence that excellent ſaying of <hi>Ephraem Syrus,</hi> when he came to die; <hi>In my whole Life</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached my Lord and Maſter, nor ſuffered any fooliſh Talk to come out of my Lips; nor did I ever Curſe or Revile any Man, or maintain the leaſt Difference or Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie with any Chriſtian in all my Life.</hi> Why may it not be among us, as Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Temple</hi> ſays it is in the <hi>Netherlands?</hi> where differences in Opinions, make none in Affections; little in Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where it ſerves but for Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Variety: They argue without Intereſt or Anger, they differ without Enmity or Scorn, and they agree without Confederacy. Men live together like Citizens of the World, aſſociated by the common tyes of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49606:43"/>and the Bonds of Peace, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Impartial Protection of indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Laws, with equal encouragement of all Arts and Induſtry, and equal free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Speculation and Enquiry. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our old ſaying, <hi>Soft Words and hard Arguments are the beſt;</hi> and if I may judge of others by my ſelf, harſh Expreſſions and a ſowre Carriage, will never make one regard what another ſays: The Potion has too much Gall in it to be Medicinal; whereas we cannot refuſe to liſten to a Man, that comes to us in a mild and gentle manner. It is the Spirit of <hi>Elias</hi> and not the Spirit of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that is furious and violent. It is an Human thing to be kind to thoſe of the ſame nature with our ſelves; but for one Profeſſing Religion, to be furious and eager and ſtormy, is to let the Chriſtian deſtroy the Man. Mildneſs is an Offspring of Heaven, the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of Chriſt, and has a ſtrange con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining Power with it: A calm and gentle Soul will govern and allay the diſorder of the Tongue, and keep us all
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49606:44"/>quiet. The very appearances (as one obſerves) of a calm Temper have a Charm in them; but the effects of them in concurrence with other pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Methods are almoſt irreſiſtible: And, ſays he, it is better to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run and ruined in the ways of Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, than to conquer all the World by Cruelty; in the one we bear the Croſs, and ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake, in the other we Triumph in the Garments of Antichriſt, dyed red with the Blood of thoſe, who though in Errors, yet may be good Men in the main, for ought we know.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>Let us always Love our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, though we cannot he in all things of their Mind:</hi> And this Love will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all thoſe acts of Kindneſs and good Will which I have newly mentioned; in our different places of Worſhip, and in the different manner of our Prayers, there may be ſtill an Union in our Hearts. I can love many a good Man and wiſh him well with all my Soul, to whoſe particular Perſuaſion I am not
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49606:44"/>ſatisfied to joyn my ſelf. Let us love our Brethren for the <hi>Common Truths,</hi> in which they and we both agree; we have <hi>one Faith,</hi> though we have two Names; then let us commend all that we ſee in others, that is truly good and commendable; let us commend their Gifts and Graces, their Learning and their Holy Lives; let us pity their Faults, and praiſe them for their good Deeds; and this is the beſt way that I know of, to keep us from falling out: And if we muſt ſtrive, let us ſtrive who ſhall be moſt ſerviceable to God, and to one another.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>Take heed of loving need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Diſputations:</hi> Of all things beware of taking pleaſure in them; or of <hi>fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous and curious Queſtions,</hi> which tend to fill us with Rancour, but promote not Edification. Carnal Zeal (as one ſays) may put us on diſputing, but true Zeal will put us upon Prayer. Some Men are of ſo ſtrange a Palate, that they love Niceties and <hi>Quelques choſe,</hi> rather than ſolid and ſubſtantial
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49606:45"/>Food; ſome love to ſplinter the plain Truths of the Goſpel, and to wrap them up in Clouds, when, if they left them to their native plainneſs, they would be as bright as day. For my part, I had rather be a <hi>quiet Ploughman,</hi> than a <hi>fiery Philoſopher;</hi> I had rather be a Son of Peace, than the greateſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puter in the World: Diſputes occaſion abundance of ferment in the Minds of thoſe, who would otherwiſe be very quiet People; and they alſo prove a Generation of Vipers: Such as love them, generally ſting one another with many baſe and mean Reflections, and which taſt more of <hi>Billings-gate,</hi> than of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> I thank God I have a peculiar Antipathy in my Temper to all hot and fiery Proceedings, and I had rather Preach <hi>one Sermon of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Brethren, than Write a thouſand <hi>Follo's of Controverſie.</hi> We have all Reaſon to be thankful that our Age is pretty well delivered from a doting Admiration of the old School-men, that ſpun Divinity into Cobwebs, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49606:45"/>made Depths and Myſteries where they found none; it would pity a Man to ſee ſuch excellent parts as many of them had, to be ſo ill imployed: But their Notions are now muſty and antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and dead, and I will never do any thing to revive or quicken them: For as one very well obſerves, our Fathers in the beginning of the Reformation, were greatly ſcandalized at that <hi>School divinity,</hi> which for a long time had fill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the World, not only with Queſtions vain and frivolous, but pernicious alſo, and leading Men to Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. What can any one think of ſuch a manner of treating the Myſteries of Religion as they uſed, and by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions crude and ſenſleſs, if it were not that all that was very likely to raiſe an abundance of Errors, and excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrived for the maintaining of all ſuch, as Ignorance, Paſſion, Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or Intereſts would have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced? One of the Effects of that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order of the Schools was the deprav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſtian Morality by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49606:46"/>of divers deſtructive Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims, which tended only to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Men's Minds and Hearts; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of which ſee at large in <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur</hi> Claude<hi>'s Hiſtorical Defence of the Reformation, part</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 28. It would be a Comfortable Sight to ſee the Funeral of all <hi>needleſs Controverſies.</hi> We have ſeen indeed a Book lately writ by a Learned Man,
<note place="margin">Mr. Baxter.</note> of <hi>The End of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies;</hi> and I wiſh they were really ended, that ſo we might Learn though not to Talk ſo logically, yet to Live better. Some Errors there are indeed that muſt be oppoſed, and God leaves not his Miniſters without Gifts for that very Purpoſe. <hi>The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Church of</hi> England <hi>have done worthily in their excellent and Learned Writings againſt Popery;</hi> they have ſhewed their feebler Adverſaries the Papiſts, what Learning and a good Cauſe was able to produce, to their ſolid Reſutation. And I may add, The Diſſenters too have done their
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49606:46"/>part againſt theſe Philiſtines, though they have been by the ſeverity of ſome later Years very much diſcouraged, yet none will deny but ſuch as Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Clarkſon,</hi> and many other Divines among us have done very conſiderable Service in their Learned Books againſt the Common Enemy.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Do not attribute the Judgments of God, that may befal us all, to this or that Party:</hi> There is no doubt but we are all guilty of many Provocations in the Sight of God. Do not ſay, this or that Evil is long of the <hi>Conformiſts;</hi> nor ought they to ſay this or that befals us, becauſe there are ſo many <hi>Diſſenters:</hi> This would be in too great Meaſure to imitate the Heathens, in the Time of the firſt Perſecutions, who if there were any pinching Famine, or any contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Diſeaſe, that over-ran <hi>Italy,</hi> or if the River <hi>Tyber</hi> did overflow his Bounds, and cauſe abundance of Damage to the Country by that means, it was imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately the Clamour of the People, That
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49606:47"/>the Chriſtians were the cauſe of all theſe Evils, and that the Gods were angry with them for ſuffering the Chriſtian Religion: Thus pretending by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable Impudence, to know the certain Cauſe of God's Judgments, which are a great deep, and the laying the Blame only on one ſide, does neceſſarily make People quarrel with one another, whereas upon all ſuch Occaſions there ought to be among them a common and ſincere Humiliation.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>We ought to ſtudy our own Hearts more, and what Work we have to do there, and then we ſhould not ſo eaſily fall out with one another.</hi> Alas, if we have enough to do within, with our own Thoughts, with our own Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, with our own Sins, what Time ſhall we have to range abroad, and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to meddle and interpoſe in the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Opinions of other People? We ſhall have no time to cenſure when we find that we our ſelves are bad enough.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:49606:47"/>
            <p>In order to accompliſh this, let us</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſider</hi> I. <hi>How many things all good Chriſtians and Proteſtants are agreed in:</hi> We are all agreed, That God is our only Happineſs, and Chriſt our only Saviour, and the Spirit our only Sanctifier. We are all agreed, That Heaven is our Home, and Holineſs, the way thither. We are all agreed, That the Scripture is the Rule of our Faith, and that Sin, the World and the Devil are our great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Enemies; why ſhould we not bear with one another in things that are of a much lower nature than theſe great and weighty Matters of the Law? For (as one of our Learned Biſhops expreſſes it) The very Baſis of the <hi>Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> is this,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Biſh.</hi> Patrick<hi>'s Serm. before the Queen, on</hi> Col. 3.15. <hi>p.</hi> 36.</note> That <hi>all neceſſary Truths are not only plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Holy Scriptures, but plainly ſet down there:</hi> Which ſingle Truth being agreed, it is manifeſt there muſt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49606:48"/>needs be an Union of Opinions among us in all things neceſſary: And as for other things which are not evident in Holy Scriptures, and therefore are not neceſſary, what ſhould hinder, but that notwithſtanding any different Opinions about them, there be among us a Unity of Affection; unto which the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures direct and preſs us, as the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Happineſs of which this World is capable? We have all the ſame Creed, and we all ſubſcribe to the ſame <hi>Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Articles,</hi> except ſome ſmall Points relating to the Ceremonies. Let but the Miniſters of all ſides ſtrive, as Mr. <hi>Dod</hi> uſed to expreſs it, to preach Chriſt into the Hearts of their Hearers, and then they will love as his Subjects, and as Heirs of the ſame Glory, and bear with one another. How much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon agreed Work have we all to do? How many ignorant People to inſtruct? How many Wounded to Heal? How many Troubled in Soul to reſolve and pacify? How many Sleepers to a waken? How many Wanderers to reduce into
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49606:48"/>the Right Way? And is all this Work upon our Hands, and have we any Time to loſe in Quarrelling and <hi>Falling out by the Way?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider. 2. <hi>Whenever the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and proſperous Condition of the Church ſhall be manifeſted, it will be introduced by Peace, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Love will then abound.</hi> Iſ. 11.6. <hi>The wolf ſhall dwell with the lamb, and the Leopard ſhall lye down with the kid, and the calf and the young lion, and the fatling together, and a little Child ſhall lead them,</hi> &amp;c. v. 9. <hi>They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy Mountain; for the earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the ſea.</hi> Ezek. 28.24. <hi>There ſhall be no more a pricking brier unto the houſe of Iſrael, nor any griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thorn of all that are round about them, that deſpiſed them, and they ſhall know that I am the Lord God.</hi> Zech. 14.9. <hi>The Lord ſhall be King over all the earth, in that day ſhall there be one Lord, and his name One.</hi> A glorious
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49606:49"/>Light ſhall ſhine from Heaven, and ſhall ſhew to all good People the Right and the Comely Way of Peace; the Spirit of the Lord ſhall reconcile thoſe Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that are now ſomewhat ſtrange to one another; then the Luſtre of Chriſtianity, which is now obſcured with our Contentions, ſhall appear in all its Brightneſs and all that look upon the Church then, ſhall diſcern it to be full of Glory: It ſhall no more appear in Garments died in Blood, mangled and torn by open Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and falſe Friends, but in Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Praiſe, and then be very Beautiful without, as well as ſhe is now within. Then <hi>Zion ſhall be a praiſe throughout the earth.</hi> Then ſhall the golden Age of Peace return again, then ſhall the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> deſcend from Heaven; nay then Heaven it ſelf ſhall come down to this Earth, and our now deformed World ſhall then have an Amiable and comely Face; <hi>Then the Tabernacle of God ſhall be with men, and he will dwell
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49606:49"/>with them.</hi> And my Friends, do we hear of ſuch pleaſant Things, and ſuch glorious Times, and do we not all wiſh to ſee theſe joyful days begin to dawn? Do we wiſh, and ſhall we not endeavour by our Prayers, and by our Love, to make this bleſſed and comfortable Time to haſten on apace? Surely 'tis Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive enough to ſay, it will be then a <hi>Time of Love.</hi> Come then let us lay aſide all Backbiting and Reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and Heats and Quarrels, with one another; come my Friends, my Brethren, and my Fellow-Travellers, God is willing to forgive us all our former Sins and Provocations, let us I beſeech you forgive one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Let there not be one in this Aſſembly, that harbours a rancorous revengeful Thought againſt any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever: Let us not <hi>Fall out by the Way,</hi> for we hope to dwell in Peace at our Journeys end, we hope all to come to the ſame Heaven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> let us rejoyce in each other's Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare;
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49606:50"/>let us relieve each other's Wants, and in fine, let us unite our Hearts, our Praiſes and our Thoughts, to God our Maker, who is the God of Peace; and as our Apoſtle ſays, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.16. <hi>The Lord of Peace him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf give you Peace always by all Means.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſid.</hi> 3. Not falling out by the way will increaſe the number of good People: Union among Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren is in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.3. ſaid to be <hi>as the Dew of Hermon, and as the Dew that deſcended upon the Mountain of Zion,</hi> i. e. as one very well Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſes upon it, without Dew nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Hermon</hi> nor <hi>Zion</hi> would be any other than very barren Places; ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Concord, our Life would be very miſerable. The dew falling from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, covered thoſe places with Herbs and Plants and Fruits; Brotherly love makes the Church to flouriſh in Zeal and Patience and Diligence and Fervour; and it is a very great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49606:50"/>to New Converts, when they can ſay <hi>of the</hi> old ones, Behold, <hi>How theſe good People love one another!</hi> There is nothing in all the World has ſo great a Magnetiſm and ſuch an attractive Vertue as Love; 'tis the moſt mild and gentle of all the Paſſions, and ſo conſequently the moſt powerful and perſuaſive: What a Sweetneſs and a Pleaſure is there in a Family, where the ſeveral Members of it treat one another, with a cordial and ſincere Affection? How ambitions is every one to be acquainted with ſuch a Loving Company? But at what a diſtance will others keep from a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety where there is no Agreement, but an everlaſting Fighting and Scolding with one another? To live in Unity and Peace, would bring again that happy Temper, which was common every where, when <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32. <hi>The Multitude of them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, were of one Heart and one Soul,</hi> when they called one another
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49606:51"/>Brethren and lived as ſuch, and were full of Condecenſion, and Charity, and good Works; for then, as ſome obſerve,
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Horneck</hi>'s Letter conc. the Primitive Chriſt. p. 498</note> Religion had mortified in the Rich and Noble all Punctilo's of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſtate, and made them remember that in Chriſt they were all equal. She in whoſe Veins the nobleſt Blood did run, would ſay of her poor diſtreſſed Neighbour, ſhe is my Siſter, my Fellow-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, one that hath part in my dear Redeemer; if ſhe be Ancient, ſhe is my Mother, ſaid ſhe; if Younger, ſhe is my Daughter: Nor were theſe Expreſſions, Names of courſe only, but they were Written in their Hearts, and their Lips ſpoke what their Minds believed, and theſe Words were at once pronounced and thought. If, as he ſays, one Family had any thing to do more than ordinary,
<note place="margin">Id. p. 520.</note> the Neighbouring Family would help them: If one was to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49606:51"/>Faſt, his Neighbour Faſted with him; if one Wept, his Neighbour did Weep with him; if one Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, his Neighbour Mourned with him, as if both had committed the ſame Sin; they had their Joys and Sorrows common, and they might be ſaid to be all in one, and one in all. In theſe loving and amiable Times, by theſe gentle and kind Methods, many thouſands were added to the Church: Whereas, for Brethren to fall out, is very ſcandalous and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graceful; it makes the Religion they profeſs, look very meanly in the eyes of Strangers. When they ſee that it does not reconcile their Minds to one another, they have not Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment nor Patience enough to examin its abſtruſer Myſteries, but what effects it produces they do moſt nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly obſerve; and if it avail not ſo far as to make Men peaceable, they conclude it does them no good at all. 'Tis a thing more eſpecially ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to the People, when they ſee
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49606:52"/>thoſe Miniſters diſagree, and thoſe Lights daſh againſt one another, which ſhould yield a pleaſant, an united, and a Common Light; therefore Chriſt prayed to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.23. <hi>Let them be made perfect in one, that the World may know that thou haſt ſent me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſid. 4. <hi>Not to falll out by the Way would be a great joy to your Miniſters;</hi> they would ſtudy their Sermons and Preach them with more Comfort, if they had always to deal with a Peaceable and a Loving People; nay, they would have more Time wherein to ſtudy; for ſeveral Hours una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably go away in ſtriving to Compoſe Differences, when their Hearers are ſo fooliſh as to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with one another; and then they are a great Interruption and Grief to them in their moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Retirement, and many Times
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49606:52"/>their Bitterneſs and Wrath ſend them ſooner to the Grave.</p>
            <p>Conſid. 5. <hi>Falling out by the Way, and bitter Contentions amongſt thoſe that ſhould Love as Brethren, may ſtir up the Wrath of God againſt them all.</hi> It is no Wonder if a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, after long Patience, be at laſt provoked to turn all his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren out of Doors, when they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be quiet, nor agree together: So it was heretofore, when there was in the Church great Siding one againſt another, Paſtor againſt Paſtor, and People againſt People, ſome ingaged in this Faction, ſome in that, till, as one obſerves, the <hi>Brethren of the Camp</hi> brought in <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian's</hi> Perſecution, which devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them all: And it has often been obſerved, by Learned Men, That when God had bleſſed his Church with Peace and Protection, and after a long tryal, during three Ages and ten Perſecutions, a nurſing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49606:53"/>was raiſed up: Then aroſe thoſe Conteſts about ſeveral Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative and Myſtical Points, which made the Churches of <hi>Africa</hi> very deſolate; and what wonderful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries were occaſioned by the too warm and eager Contentions of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Church? This fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out has turned the moſt pleaſant and fruitful Countries into a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and the moſt beautiful Churches into Duſt and Aſhes.</p>
            <p>Conſid. 6. <hi>'Tis one of the Great Deſigns of the Goſpel of our Saviour, to promote Peace among all his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers.</hi> Nothing does he more urge than that they ſhould Love one another; and as he had loved them with the moſt conſtant and ſincere Affection: And for this he prayed, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.21. <hi>That they all may be one, as thou Father art in me and I in in thee, that they all ſo may be one in us.</hi> His firſt Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance was wellcom'd by the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49606:53"/>Heavenly Hoſt with Songs of Love, ſaying, <hi>Glory to God in the higheſt, peace upon earth, and good Will to Men.</hi> And to be full of Love is to be <hi>Angelical;</hi> it is a Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of their kind and Loving Nature: And which is more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, it is the very Image of the Son of God, who is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Image of his Father: And <hi>God</hi> we know <hi>is Love.</hi> The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel does frequently urge us to live in Peace and Quietneſs, and conveys to us that Spirit which is to mortifie our bitter and unruly Paſſions: And the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> where our Lord does intend at laſt to bleſs all his Servants, is the City of Peace; and his Sacraments are deſigned to bind us more to himſelf, and to one another in the trueſt Bonds of Love. We have one Baptiſm, and are all nouriſhed with the ſame Bread from Heaven; he entertains all at the ſame Table, that we may lay aſide all our little Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49606:54"/>when we ſee him ſhedding his deareſt Blood to appeaſe his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Wrath, and to teſtifie how he loved us all.</p>
            <p>Conſid. 7. <hi>You ought not to fall out by the Way, for you will very ſhortly be at your Journey's End.</hi> This is the Motive of our Apoſtle, <hi>Let your moderation be known unto all Men, the Lord is at hand,</hi> Phil. 4.5. The Lord is at hand, who is to judge you and them; The Lord is at hand that will bleſs you for ever, if you are peaceable, and meek, and lowly; but he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domn you if he find that by Wrath, and Strife, and Contention you are altogether diſagreeable to his Holy Example. Oh let not the Great Judge find you quarrelling with one another, when he comes, but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>to be found of him in Peace.</hi> Surely the Brethren of <hi>Joſeph</hi> might keep from <hi>falling out by the Way,</hi> when it was but a little Diſtance
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49606:54"/>between <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Canaan:</hi> It would have been a very unpleaſant thing to their good Father, to have ſeen them coming Home in ſo bad a Temper. Oh my Friends, let us heartily love one another; let us do all we can for one another: It is but a little Seaſon that we are to be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; a little while hence, we that are in this Congregation ſhall be in the Congregation of the Dead, and <hi>our Places,</hi> and our Friends <hi>know us no more.</hi> Oh let us not be Clamorous now againſt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſeeing we ſhall ſhortly be in the ſilent Grave: Surely we that have ſo ſhort and ſo vain a Life, and may ſo ſoon be dead, ſhould ſpend our Time to better Purpoſe than to quarrel or fall out; People that are to die together do uſually embrace one another with all the Marks of a tender Affection, juſt before they die. Let us labour to die in Charity with all the World, for Death will come upon us all,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49606:55"/>and we muſt reſt together in the Grave; there will be no Warmth, no Fire in our Common Duſt, there will be no Fighting or Scolding in the Grave; there lye the Heads, now Cool enough, that were once full of Heat, and many a Vexatious and Uneaſie Thought, and who once diſturbed both themſelves and others with needleſs Diſputations, and Strife, and Quarrels. Oh let us be as Loving Travellers, that are all going to the ſame Bleſſed Home, and let us help one another in the Way thither, ſeeing it is but for a little while, and we know we have but a little way to go, and when we are at our Journey's End, our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father will moſt kindly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain us all.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only ſay two or three things relating to the particular Occaſion, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:49606:55"/>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>To the Relations of our Deceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Friend.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>To the Young Men that were his Acquaintance. And</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, <hi>To thoſe who are uſually Hearers in this Place.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> You that are <hi>his Relations</hi> have loſt a kind Relation and a good Friend; you that heard him diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and ſaw him with Delight, ſhall not ſee him again till <hi>the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens be no more.</hi> You have laid him in the Grave, and there his poor Body does now conſume away: But let his Death, and the Death of your other Friends teach you to prepare to Dye; as you now Mourn for him, ſo will others Mourn for you, when a few Days and Nights are gone. Oh make you ſure of a better World, for this is altogether Vanity: Breath after Eternal Life, for this that you
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49606:56"/>now have, does very quickly paſs away. And let me beſeech you earneſtly to long for that Day, when you and your Holy Friends ſhall meet in Health together, and never part again; when you ſhall ſee thoſe that you beheld here pale and wan with Sickneſs, to ſhine like the Sun in Glory; when you ſhall ſee thoſe Breaſts, from whence there came ſo many Sighs and Groans in their painful dying Agonies, to be full of Love and Praiſe: You ſhall never hear their Tongues faulter with a Diſeaſe, nor their Breath ſtop, nor ſee their Countenances change, they ſhall never complain nor die again; they ſhall be with you, and you with them, and all of you with the ſame God and the ſame Jeſus, and ſhall never quit or be ſeparated from one another. Oh bleſſed State! Oh ſweet and comfortable Priviledge of all true Believers! What is all that ſhines in this World to the leaſt Beam of this Approaching Glory? You
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49606:56"/>have loſt a dear Relation, and one whom, if our Prayers could have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, we would have kept longer with us. I beſeech you, ſee that you have an Intereſt in a God, whom you may never loſe. You that attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him and viſited him in his Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, have beheld his Patience, and ſeen his Reſignation. In the many Times that I viſited him, I never heard him in the leaſt <hi>murmur</hi> at the Hand of God, though it preſſed him very ſore; he never in the leaſt opened his mouth to complain that his Diſeaſe was ſo tedious and ſo very long; imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate you his Patience when you come to the like Trials, and ſhew your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Will of God, who has now taken your Dear Friend away. Some of us that were near him in his dying Agonies, heard him praying earneſtly to God through Jeſus Chriſt, and expreſſing his Truſt in his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs alone, and hoping only for Acceptance in and through this Great Mediator; and indeed let
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49606:57"/>Men in Health and at a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as they think from Death, talk what they will of the great Power of their own Will, or of the exactneſs and multitude of their own Works, yet the approach of Judgment will ſtrangely change their Apprehenſions, and let them know, that the Mercy of God in Chriſt is the beſt Plea when they are to die. Some of you were Sick at the ſame time, and the Phyſicians had no hope of your Recovery, but God has been your Healer: God has tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned your Glaſs when his is run out; and whilſt you are in Time, he is in Eternity: God has renewed your Life, and taken his away; his Lamp is gone out, and yours is recruited with freſh Oyl again. Let the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Goodneſs and Deliverance of ſo kind a Phyſician, draw you near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to himſelf; and whilſt you ſee our departed Friend and your Son no more in your Habitation, beg of God to dwell with you <hi>there;</hi> he is better
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49606:57"/>than a <hi>thouſand Sons and Daughters,</hi> his Preſence and his Favour is a part of Heaven. God may have ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you with this deſign, that you may more glorifie him by a patient acquieſcence in his Will, and I do not queſtion but you do. Let me further entreat you his Relations to continue to live in Love, for your Friend has left you all this <hi>Legacy.</hi> And if at any time by any occaſion whatſoever you are tempted to Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, remember your dead Friend as if you heard him ſay, <hi>Fall not ought by the way:</hi> Theſe were the Words left in a ſolemn manner by a <hi>dying Man,</hi> and I hope you and we all ſhall the more regard them upon that Account: Excellent Advice he has given us, God give us the Grace to take it. It is neceſſary to be conſidered by many People in the World, That, to their own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, never Quarrel more than about the <hi>Laſt Will and Teſtament</hi> of a Departed Friend, and make
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49606:58"/>that an Occaſion of long and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Suits at Law, which was deſigned to put an End to all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies and Debates: But there is not the leaſt Cauſe to fear any thing of this from any of you, you have not ſo learned Chriſt: Go on in your peaceable Carriage and Behaviour, and the <hi>God of Peace</hi> ſhall be with you, and he himſelf will ſupply this and all your other Wants.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>To thoſe Young Men that were the Acquaintance of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Mr.</hi> Dunwell. Oh what Cauſe have you to admire the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Goodneſs of God, that when ſo many are ſnatch'd away, that you have known, he ſtill ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers you to Live, when many that were both Healthful and Stronger, and Younger than you but a while agoe, are at their Journey's End, and you are ſtill Travelling in the Way: You have yet Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49606:58"/>and days of Grace wherein to work out your Salvation, and to prepare for another World; and let me deſire you that are as yet in your Flouriſhing and Greeneſt Youth not to <hi>put afar off the Evil Day;</hi> do not grieve the Spirit of God; do not miſimprove your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, nor loſe your Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for you may be near, very near to your latter end; in a Week or a Fortnight, or a Months time, you may be alſo in your Eternity: It is yet Morning with you, and as yet 'tis a clear Day, but Storms will overtake you, and for ought you know your <hi>Sun may go down at Noon:</hi> Oh! learn to be Wiſe in the Time of Health, for Sickneſs is not the moſt proper Seaſon wherein to do any thing for your Souls; your uneaſineſs, your diſorder and your pains will then be ſo great, that you'll find your Selves unable to do any thing that requires much Thought and Care; thoſe of us
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49606:59"/>that have been Sick, can tell you this by <hi>our own ſaid Experience,</hi> an thoſe that are now Sick will Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm to you the very ſame thing: Think you hear this your Depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Friend ſaying to you, Oh! do not preſume upon having a very long Life, for you ſee God has cut me off in the midſt of my Days: <q>Oh! never think that you can too ſoon be Religious, or that you can do too much for God, for he is worthy to be Served: Whileſt you mind the World, Oh! take heed that you do not forget Heaven and Eternal Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Remember that your Time haſtens on apace; Oh! Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that Sickneſs will come to you as it came to me; reſtleſs Nights and weary Days will be your Lot, as they were mine a while ago: Death will ſoon knock at your Door, as he knockt at mine, and painful Agonies will go before him, and none but
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49606:59"/>thoſe that have felt them know what are the Pangs of Death.</q> O my Friends! Do you know <hi>what it is to Die?</hi> Do ye know what it is to appear before the Tribunal of an Omniſcient and Infinitely Holy God, and will you not make ready for it? Oh! repent of all your Follies, Pray in Secret, Examin any Try your ſelves, and put your Souls in Order that it may be well with you for ever-more. I beg of you that are Young to conſider the <hi>Example</hi> and the <hi>Practice</hi> of our <hi>Deceaſed Friend;</hi> he was not of their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that ſpend all their Mony on their Cloaths, or in Games and Taverns, and needleſs and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Recreations, but gave ſome part of what he had to <hi>Encourage and Promote the Goſpel;</hi> he was (which I put upon him as a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Mark of Honour) <hi>a great Friend to young Miniſters;</hi> he knew, tho many others never conſidered it, that the young Men came to
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49606:60"/>appear in the World with great Diſcouragements, and after having undergone many great and ſharp Neceſſities, and he always was ready to aſſiſt them what he could, and I queſtion not but therein he performed an acceptable Service un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>God.</hi> When we had a Lecture in <hi>Exchange-Ally</hi> he was forward to help us all he could there, and the continuance of many Years and very rugged and ſevere Times never changed his Temper, but as he was then, ſo he continued to be our Friend to <hi>his Dying day.</hi> He gave us more than a <hi>Cup of cold Water,</hi> and I hope he has now a <hi>Prophet's Reward:</hi> And are there none of you that might ſave a great deal of Mony from need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Expences, from Luxury and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and Recreation, to encourage <hi>the Miniſters of the Goſpel?</hi> And I think I might ſay to thoſe <hi>Young-men that are our conſtant Hearers,</hi> that I hope it would be no diſhonour to them
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49606:60"/>hereafter, to be called Encouragers <hi>of the Lecture at</hi> Crosby-Square; and I would not ſpeak only to the Young, but to the Aged and the Rich; it would more Honour your Memory, and make your Slumbers in the Grave more quiet, if you made <hi>your own Hands Executors,</hi> and gave yearly ſuch a part of your Eſtate to the <hi>Maintenance of poor Young Scholars and Miniſters:</hi> You do not know but by that means, you might promote the Converſion of many Souls, which would be <hi>your Joy in the day of the Lord:</hi> As for you that are <hi>Aged,</hi> bleſs God that you have ſo long a Day, and ſee that your Sins be not more than thoſe of others that have a ſhorter date. Here is a Young Man dead in the middle of his Days, and ſo have you ſeen many others die; Oh! take heed that you be not old in Sin, take heed that all your work be done, for your Clock begins to point to the concluding Twelve;
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49606:61"/>your Glaſs has remaining in it but a very little Sand; your Sun is going down, the Shadows of the Evening are ſtretched out upon the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and in a few Moments it will be Night with you, when you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Work: Take heed that when the Grave opens to receive you, your Sins do not lye down with you in the Duſt. To <hi>all of you that are here,</hi> let this Warning be of Uſe: Our Friend a few Weeks ago, was a <hi>conſtant Attender in this Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and now he is at his long Home: He uſed to ſit with Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Seriouſneſs in this Place, but now he will never ſee us, nor we him, till the great Day. He that ſilled a Seat here, does now fill a Grave; a Coffin holds him there, whom nothing could detain from Religious Aſſemblies while he was alive: But we hope that he is gone to a better, a more enlightned, a more loving, and a more pure Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, even the <hi>Aſſembly of the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49606:61"/>Firſt-born, and the Spirits of juſt Men made perfect.</hi> His Relations have loſt a loving Relation, his Friends a kind Acquaintance, his Servants a good Maſter, and we a liberal Benefactor; and we may juſtly cry and ſay, O Death thou doſt indeed make great ſpoil and havock in the World; thou doſt viſit every Family and every Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at one time or other; thou art ſo cruel that thou ſpareſt neither Young nor Old, neither the Uſeleſs nor the Serviceable, neither the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable nor Unprofitable Servant: Our Sin has indeed given thee all thy Power, and made thee look with a formidable Aſpect to Fleſh and Blood; but becauſe thou art ſo formidable, we turn our Eyes from thee, and look with more pleaſure upon that Bleſſed Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that has diſarmed thee of all thy hurtful Power, and that will give us Life when thou haſt exerciſed all thy Rage, and done the very
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49606:62"/>worſt; he dyed that that ſuch as believe might never die. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſomewhat fear thee, O Death, as thou doſt diſſolve our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Frame; but we bid thee wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, as thou art the Meſſenger of the Lord of Glory to convey us thither.</p>
            <p>To Conclude, It is like that we who are in this Aſſembly upon this occaſion, ſhall never meet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; Oh that We and all our Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance might meet in Heaven above! And let us be ſure not to <hi>Fall out in our Way</hi> thither: Let us while we live in a changeable and fading World, prepare for one that will never fade: Let us not be amazed at the Grave, it now ſwal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lows us up and our Friends; but it ſhall not keep us very long, for our Lord will ſhortly come and make our Duſt to live again, and make thoſe Bodies that were weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by Sickneſs and deſtroyed by
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49606:62"/>Death, to be like his own glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Body; and what we now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, we ſhall then ſee and know to be true: In the mean while let us make Conſcience of Meditating at the leaſt once a day, upon that Comfortable and Reviving Place of our Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14. and ſo to the end, <hi>For if we believe that Jeſus died, and roſe again, even ſo them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus, will God bring with him. For this we ſay unto you by the Word of the Lord, that we which are alive, and remain unto the coming of the Lord, ſhall not prevent them which are aſleep. For the Lord himſelf, ſhall deſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, with the Voice of the Archangel, and with the Trump of God; and the dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt: Then we which are alive, and remain, ſhall be caught up together with them in the Clouds, to meet the Lord in the Air; and ſo ſhall we be ever be with the Lord. Wherefore Comfort one another with
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49606:63"/>theſe Words.</hi> I conclude this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject with the Prayer of the ſame Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Now the Lord of Peace himſelf, give you Peace always by all Means.</hi> The <hi>Lord be with you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:49606:63"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>John Dunton</hi> at the <hi>Raven</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> viz.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Mourners Companion:</hi> Or Funeral Diſcourſes on ſeveral Texts, by <hi>John Shower,</hi> p. 1<hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Life and Death of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>John Eliot,</hi> the firſt Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Goſpel to the Heathens in <hi>America.</hi> Written by Mr. <hi>Cotton Mather.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Barker</hi>'s Book, Intituled, <hi>Flores Intellectuales,</hi> or Select No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Sentences, and Obſervations:
<pb facs="tcp:49606:64"/>Collected out of ſeveral Authors.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Lees</hi> Joy of Faith.</p>
            <p>Caſuiſtical Morning-Exerciſe, the Fourth Volume. By ſeveral Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in and about <hi>London;</hi> preached in <hi>October</hi> 1689.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Quick</hi>'s Young Man's Claim to the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Crow</hi>'s Vanity of Judicial A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrology.</p>
            <p>A New Martyrology, or the Bloody Aſſizes, containing the Lives and Sufferings of thoſe who died in the Weſt. The third Edition.</p>
            <p>Early Piety Exemplified, in the Life and Death of Mr. <hi>Nathaniel Mather:</hi> With a Prefactory Epiſtle by Mr. <hi>Matthew Mead.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49606:64"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Poetical Fragments.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Oakes</hi> Funeral Sermon.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Kent</hi>'s Funeral Sermon.</p>
            <p>The Tragedies of Sin, together with the Remarks on the Life of the great <hi>Abraham.</hi> By <hi>Stephen Jay,</hi> Rector of <hi>Chimer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Heads of Agreement aſſented to by the United Miniſters.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>There is now in the Preſs.</head>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Brand</hi>'s Funeral Sermon, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Dr. <hi>Anneſley,</hi> which will ſpeedily be Publiſh'd. Printed for <hi>John Dunton.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
